<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of Gods free grace, and mans free will</title>
            <author>Perkins, William, 1558-1602.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15264</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841651</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176348</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240901380</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 19750</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S105926</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99841651e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15264)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176348)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1328:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of Gods free grace, and mans free will</title>
                  <author>Perkins, William, 1558-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 184 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601. And are to be sold at the signe of the Crowne in Pauls churchybard by Simon Waterson.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Perkins.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of mans free will, and Gods free grace.</note>
                  <note>Pages 28-9, 48 and 135 misnumbered 48-9, 47 and 137.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; several pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176348:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176348:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> TREATISE of Gods free grace, and <hi>mans free will.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>HINC LVCEM ET POCVLA SACRA</p>
               <p>ALMA MATER CANTA BRIGIA</p>
            </figure>
            <p>PRINTED BY IOHN <hi>Legat, Printer to the Vniuersitie</hi> of Cambridge. 1601.</p>
            <p>And are to be sold at the signe of the Crowne in Pauls Churchyard by Simon Waterson.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176348:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176348:2"/>
            <head>To the Right <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, Sir Edward</hi> Denie, Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, it is a thing most euident, that the present Religion of the Church of Rome is an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emie to the grace of God, two waies. First, because it exalts the libertie of mans will, and extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates the grace of God: and this it doth in fiue respects. For first of all it teacheth, that naturall freewill of man hath in it not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Passiue or potentiall, but also an Actiue power, or imperfect strength in duties of godlines: and so much the lesse power is as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to the grace of God. This doctrine of theirs is flat against reason. For, the will of man in it selfe is a naturall thing: and therefore it is neither fit nor able to effect
<pb facs="tcp:176348:3"/> any supernaturall action (as all actions of godlines are) vnles it be first of all (as they say) eleuated aboue his condition by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of a supernaturall habit. And the Scripture is vtterly against this doctrine, when it saith, <hi>Ye were once darknesse,</hi> Eph. 5.8. <hi>We are not sufficient of our selues to thinke any thing of our selues,</hi> 2. Cor. 3.5. <hi>The naturall man</hi> [that is, he that wants the spirit of God] <hi>cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things of God,</hi> 1. Cor. 2.14. <hi>Ye were dead in sinnes and trespasses,</hi> Eph. 2.1. <hi>Without Christ and without God in the world,</hi> v. 12. Againe, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture saith further, that the heart of man is <hi>slow,</hi> Luc. 24.25. and <hi>vaine,</hi> Psal. 5.10. and <hi>hard that cannot repent,</hi> Rom. 2.5. and <hi>stonie,</hi> Ezech. 36.26. and that <hi>the Iewes were obstinate, their necke as an iron sinew, and their brow brasse,</hi> Isai. 48.4. and that it is God <hi>who giues eyes to see, and an heart to vnderstand,</hi> Deut. 29.4. By these testimonies it is manifest that grace doth not onely helpe and assist our weake nature, but altogither change the peruerse qualitie thereof, and bring it
<pb facs="tcp:176348:3"/> from darknes to light, Act. 28.18. and from death to life, Eph. 2.1. Which grace whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doth not so farre forth acknowledge, neuer yet knew what the Gospel meant: neither did he euer consider the words of our Sauiour Christ, <hi>No man comes vnto me, vnlesse the father draw him,</hi> Ioh. 6.44. <hi>Prosper</hi> the scholler of S. Augustine hath a notable saying, which I maruell that the Papists of our time doe not consider. <hi>We haue</hi> (saith he) <hi>free will by nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prosp. contra Collat. c. 18. in fine.</note>
               <hi>but for qualitie and condition it must be changed by our Lord Iesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Molina de grat. &amp; lib. arb. q. 14. art. 13. disp. 12. Gratiae auxilia, quòd efficacia sint, habent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendenter ab ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrij libertate.</note> some of the Romish religion auouch, that the efficacie of Gods preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace depends vpon the cooperation of mans will, &amp; they affirme that the Councel of Trent is of this mind: but thē to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of Paul, 1. Cor. 4.7. <hi>Who hath sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated thee?</hi> the answer may be made, I my selfe haue done it by mine owne will. And that shall be false which Paul teacheth, that beside <hi>posse-velle,</hi> the power of wel-willing, <hi>ipsum velle,</hi> that is, the act of wel-willing is of God. Phil. 2.13. Others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore place the efficacie of grace in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruitie
<pb facs="tcp:176348:4"/> of fitte obiects and perswasions: as though it were sufficient to stirre vp the heart and to incline the will in spirituall matters: and our weakenesse might be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with so easie a remedie: but God is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther said to <hi>soften the heart.</hi> Ezec. 36.26. <hi>to turne the heart,</hi> Luc. 1.17. <hi>to open the heart,</hi> Act. 16.14. And because our hearts are ouer hard, <hi>he wounds them,</hi> Cant. 4.9. <hi>he circumciseth them,</hi> Deut. 30.6. nay <hi>he bruiseth them,</hi> Ezech. 6.9. And when nothing will doe good, at length God is said <hi>to take away the stonie heart,</hi> Ezech. 11.19. <hi>to quicken them that are contrite,</hi> Isa. 57.15. Eph. 2.5. <hi>to giue a new heart,</hi> Eph. 4.23. Ezech. 36.26. nay <hi>to create a new heart,</hi> Eph. 2.10. and 4.28.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they giue vnto God in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent actions, a Depending will, whereby God wills and determines nothing but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he foresees that the will of man will determine it selfe. And thus to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the supposed Libertie of the will, that is, the indifferencie &amp; indeterminatiō ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they depriue God of his honour and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignitie.
<pb facs="tcp:176348:4"/> For by this meanes not God but will it selfe, is the first Moouer and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of her own actions.<note place="margin">Shumel. sup. 1. Thom q. 23. art. 3. disp. 8.</note> And there are euen of the Papists themselues that condemne this doctrine as a conceit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly they teach that the grace which makes vs acceptable and gratefull to God, stands in the inward gifts of the mind, specially in the gift of charitie. But this is most false which they teach: for cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is the fulfilling of the lawe: and Paul saith, we are not vnder the lawe but vnder grace. Rom. 6.14. And againe, as many as are iustified by the law, are fallen from grace. Gal. 5.4. Now the grace that doeth indeed make vs grateful to God, is the free fauour and mercie of God pardoning our sinnes in Christ, and accepting vs to eternal life, and not any qualitie in vs, as Paul sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies when he saith, we are saued not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our workes, but according to his purpose and grace, which is giuen to vs in Christ before all times. 2. Tim. 1.9.</p>
            <p>Lastly they teach that the renewed will of man, by the general direction and coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God, can performe the duties of
<pb facs="tcp:176348:5"/> godlinesse, without any speciall helpe from God by new grace. But the scripture speaks otherwise. <hi>By the grace of God I am that I am. I haue laboured, yet not I but the grace of God which is with me.</hi> 1. Cor. 10. <hi>No man can say that Iesus is the Lord, but by the holy Ghost.</hi> 1. Cor. 12.3. <hi>Without me ye can doe nothing.</hi> Ioh. 15.5. <hi>After ye beleeued, ye were sealed with the spirit.</hi> Eph. 1.17. <hi>He which hath begun this good worke in you will fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish it vntill the daie of Christ.</hi> Phil. 1.6. <hi>That ye may abound with hope by the vertue of the spirit.</hi> Rom. 15. <hi>It is God that workes in you the will and the deede.</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>Though the righteous fall he shall not be cast off: for the Lord puts vnder his hand.</hi> Psa. 37.24. <hi>Incline my heart to thy testimonies: turne away mine eies from beholding of vanitie: &amp; quicken me in thy way.</hi> Psal. 119.37. <hi>Teach me to doe thy will: because thou art my God: let thy good spirit lead me in the land of righteousnesse.</hi> Psal. 143.10. <hi>Create in me a newe heart, renewe a right spirit in me—: and stablish me
<pb facs="tcp:176348:5"/> by thy free spirit.</hi> Psal. 51.12. <hi>Draw me and I will runne after thee.</hi> By these and many other places it is euident, that God after he hath indued vs with his spirit, doth not leaue vs to be guided by our selues (for then we should fall againe to our former miserie) but he directs vs, he lifts vs vp, he leads vs, he confirmes and sustaines vs by the same grace, &amp; by the same spirit dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in vs, that walking in the way of his commandements, we may at length attaine to euerlasting happinesse.</p>
            <p>The second way whereby the Papist shews himselfe to be an enemie of the grace of God, is that he ioynes the merit of works as a Con-cause with the grace of God in that which they call the second iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in the procurement of eternall life: whereas on the contrarie Paul in the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of iustification opposeth grace to works, yea to such workes as are the gifts &amp; fruits of the spirit. For Abraham did good works not by naturall free will, but by faith. Heb. 11.8. And Paul opposeth iustifying grace to the workes of Abraham, where he saith, <hi>to him that worketh the wages is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted
<pb facs="tcp:176348:6"/> according to grace.</hi> And Tit. 3.5. <hi>Not of the workes of righteousnesse which we haue done, but of his mercy he saued vs.</hi> Rom. 11.6. <hi>If by grace, then not of workes: or els were grace no more grace.</hi> Augustine said well, that grace is no waie grace, vnlesse it be freely giuen euery way.</p>
            <p>Thus then all things considered, it is the best to ascribe all we haue or can doe that is good, wholly to the grace of God. Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is the speech of Augustine: <hi>Only hold this as a sure point of godlinesse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De lib arbit. l. 2. c. 20.</note>
               <hi>that no good thing can come either to the sense or mind, or be any way conceiued which is not of God.</hi> And Bernard: <hi>The Church shewes her selfe to be full of grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">in Cant. serm. 67.</note>
               <hi>when shee giues all shee hath to grace, namely by ascribing to it both the first and the last place. Otherwise, how is shee full of grace, if shee haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which is not of grace.</hi> Againe, <hi>I tremble to thinke any thing mine owne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horreo quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid de meo est, vt sim me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note>
               <hi>that I may be mine owne.</hi> This doctrine is the safest and the surest in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of peace of conscience, and the saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:176348:6"/> of our soules. So much the Papists them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues (betraying their owne cause) say and confesse. Bellarmine the Iesuite saith,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stificat. l. 5. c. 7.</note>
               <hi>By reason of the vncertentie of our owne iustice, &amp; for feare of falling into vaine glorie, it</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Tulissimum.</note>
               <hi>is the safest to put our whole confidence in the alone mercie and goodnesse of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cassand c. de lib. arbit.</note> Cassander in his book called the Consultation of articles in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, to Maximilian the Emperour, cites a saying of Bonauenture, which is on this manner: <hi>It is the dutie of godly mindes to ascribe nothing to themselues, but all to the grace of God. Hence it followes, that how much soeuer a man giues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grace, though in giuing many things to the grace of God, he take something from the power of nature and free will, he departes not from godlinesse: but when any thing is taken from the grace of God and giuen to nature which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to grace, there may be some dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> Thus then to hold and maintaine iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification by faith without workes, and to ascribe the whole worke of our conuersion to God, without making any diuision be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb facs="tcp:176348:7"/> grace and nature, is the safest.</p>
            <p>These things I shewe more at large in this treatise following, which I now present to your Worshippe as a small testimonie of mine humble dutie and loue: desiring you to accept the mind of the giuer, and to peruse it at your leisure. And thus I commend your Worsh. to the protection and grace of God in Christ.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worsh. in the Lord,</hi> William Perkins.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <head>A note.</head>
            <p>Pag. 109. l. 19. that some Papists place the efficacie of grace in mans will, it is the sentence of Bellarmine, de grat. &amp; lib. arb. l. 1. c. 12. <hi>Grati. vn efficacem constituunt in assensu &amp; cooperatione humana.</hi> L. Molina saith, that our will makes grace to be effectuall, De lib. arbit. p. 326, 327. and sometime againe he saith, will is but a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and no cause of the efficacie of grace. p. 329. Yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies he graunteth, that it lies in mans will whether grace shall be effectuall or no. Thus when grace is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on Gods part, will within stands as the Porter to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen or shut, or as master Controller to accept or repell the worke of God.</p>
            <p>Pag. 83. in the margin, read <hi>nihil ad non peccandum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176348:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 23.37, 38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Ierusalem, Ierusalem, which killest the Prophets, and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>est them which are sent to thee, how often would I haue gathered thy children together, as the hen gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, and ye would not!</p>
                  <p>Behold, your habitation shall be left vnto you desolate.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His whole chapter cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines a Sermon that our Sauiour Christ made to the Iewes at Ierusalem. It hath two parts. The first, is a reproofe of the Iewish Doctours, namely the Scribes and Pharisies for sundrie vices, from the beginning of the chapter to the 36. verse. The second, is an Inuectiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Ierusalem, in the words which I haue now read: <hi>Ierusalem, Ierusalem, which killest the Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> In the Inuectiue two things are to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the Rebellion of Ierusalem in the 37. verse, and the punishment of this sinne, verse 38.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:176348:8"/>
            <p>Touching the Rebellion it selfe three things are set downe, the place &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in the wordes <hi>Ierusalem, Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> the degree and practise of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in these wordes, <hi>which killest the Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> the manner and forme of their rebellion, in these words, <hi>How oft wold I haue gathered you, &amp; ye wold not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to the order of the holy Ghost, first I will begin with the place. It is a wonder that Ierusalem of all the places in the world, should be charged with the height of rebellion against God. For it was the citie of God, and had prerogatiues aboue all cities in the world.<note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> Saint Paul hath noted seuen of them. The first is, that <hi>they were Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> that is, of the posteritie of Iacob: the second is <hi>Adoption,</hi> in that they were reputed and called the children of God: the third is, that they <hi>had the glorie of God,</hi> that is, the Mercy-seat, the pledge of the presence of God: the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176348:8"/> fourth is <hi>the Couenants,</hi> that is, the two tables of the couenant: the fifth is the <hi>giuing of the law,</hi> namely of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall and ceremoniall Lawe: the sixth is, <hi>the vvorship of God,</hi> the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like solemnitie whereof was tied to the Temple at Ierusalem: the seuenth, that to them pertained the promises made to the Patriarkes touching the Messias. To these,<note place="margin">Micah 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the prophet Micah addeth the eight priuiledge, that the first Church of the New Testament, should be gathered in Ierusalem, and that consequently, the preaching of the Gospel should passe thence to all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now, for all these blessings and mercies, Christ our Sauiour cries out and complaines of Ierusalems rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And this is not the first time of his complaint. In the daies of the prophet Isai he saith,<note place="margin">Isa. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that when he had done all that he could doe for his vineyarde, it brought forth nothing but wilde
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176348:9"/> grapes.<note place="margin">Ezech. 16. all.</note> By the prophet Ezechiel he sets downe a long catalogue of his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings to this people, and withall a cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of their vnthankfulnes. Hence it appeares, that where God shewes the greatest mercie, there oftentimes is the greatest wickednes and vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And this is partly verified in this land, for within the compasse of this fourtie yeares, we haue receiued great blessings from God both for this life and for the life to come, specially the Gospel with peace and protection: and the like haue not bin seene in former ages: yet there was neuer more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes then now. For now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly men are wearie of the Gospel, and begin to decline from that which they haue bin: and the care to please God and doe his will is accounted but a curious precisenes of many.</p>
            <p>Secondly hence it may be gathered, that God doth not tie the infallible as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176348:9"/> of his spirit to any place or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men. If euer any citie in the world had this priuiledge it was Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem. But Ierusalem which was the seat and habitation of God, had not this priuiledge, because it is here cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with rebellion against God. No place therfore nor cōdition of mē hath it. It is alleadged that God hath made a promise to the order of Priesthood: <hi>the priests lips shall preserue knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 2.7.</note>
               <hi>and thou shalt require the law at his mouth.</hi> I answer, that these words are not a promise but a commandement. For sometimes wordes of the future tense are put for wordes imparatiue. And therefore the sense is this, <hi>The Priests lips shall keepe,</hi> that is, let them keepe knowledge. Againe it is alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that we are commanded to heare the Scribes and pharisies;<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> because <hi>they sit in Moses chaire.</hi> I answer, that the Chaire of Moses is not a place or seat,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176348:10"/> but the doctrine of Moses:<note place="margin">August. epist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>66.</note> and to this doctrine, I graunt, the spirit of God is annexed, when it is truly taught and beleeued. Thirdly it is alleadged, that God hath promised the spirit of truth to lead men into all truth.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13.</note> I answer, that this promise doth not directly and absolutely concerne all beleeuers, or all Ministers, but onely the Apostles, to whome it was made: and not to them for all times &amp; in all actions, but onely while they were in the Execution of their Apostolicall ministerie, which stands in the foūding of the church of the new testamēt, partly by publishing the Gospel, and partly by writing the Scriptures of the New Testament. In a word, no Scripture can be brought to prooue that, God hath, doth, or will binde his spirit to any particular place or persons. Here then falls to the ground three popish cōceits. The first, though the members of the Catholike
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176348:10"/> church may seuerally erre: yet they can not erre, when they are together in a generall Councell lawfully assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: the second, that the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre in his consistorie: the third, that personall succession is a marke of the catholike Church: which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles may be seuered from the spirit of God, as we see.</p>
            <p>Where our Sauiour Christ, vseth a repetition, saying, <hi>O Ierusalem, Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> he doth three thinges therein. First he signifies thereby that he takes it for a wonder, and for a thing incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible that the Iewes after so many blessings should be so exceedingly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull. Secondly he testifies hereby his own detestation of their vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. Thirdly by this repetition he doth awake the Iewes and stirre them vp to a serious consideration and loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this their sinne: and he doth (as it were) proclaime the same vnto vs.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176348:11"/> And not without cause: for in vnthāk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes there be two grieuous sinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, false witnes bearing, and iniustice. False witnes bearing: because the vnthankfull person denies in his heart God to be the fountaine and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the good things he hath, and he ascribes them to his owne wisdome, goodnes, strength, indeauour. Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice: because he yeelds not to God the duties, which he owes vnto him for his blessings.</p>
            <p>The second point to be considered is the degree of the Iewish rebellion. Dauid makes three degrees hereof: the first is to walke in the counsell of the vngodly, the second is to stand in the way of sinners, the third is to sit down in the skorners chaire, and this is the very top of desperate rebellion and the sinne of Ierusalem. For when Christ saith <hi>[which killest the prophets, and sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest them which are sent vnto thee]</hi> he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176348:11"/> notes out three sinnes in this citie. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitencie, whereby they perseuered in their wicked waies without hope of amendment: sacrilegious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane contempt of God &amp; the meanes of their saluation: crueltie in shedding of blood. And by crueltie I meane not one or two actions of crueltie, but an habit therein and the custome thereof: for the wordes are thus to be read, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem killing the Prophets, and sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them that are sent to thee:</hi> where stoning and killing, signifie not one acte, but a continuance and multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of acts, that is, a custome in shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of blood.</p>
            <p>It may be demāded how the Iewes should grow to this height of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. I answer thus. In euery actuall sinne there be foure things distinctly to be considered; <hi>the fault,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. culp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which is the offence of God in any action:<note place="margin">2. reatus.</note>
               <hi>the guilt</hi> or obligation to punishment for the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176348:12"/> fault:<note place="margin">3. poena.</note>
               <hi>the punishment</hi> it selfe which is death:<note place="margin">4. macula.</note>
               <hi>a blot</hi> or spot set in the foule of him that sinneth, and that by the fault or offence: and this blot is nothing els but a pronesse to the sinne committed, or to any other sinne. In the sinne of our first parents, besides the fault, guilt, punishment, there followed a blot or deformitie in the soule, which was the losse of Gods image and the dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their hearts to all manner of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills. Since the fall of Adam, he that commits an actuall offence, besides the fault, guilt, punishment, imprints in his heart a new blot and that is an increase of his naturall pronesse to sinne: euen as the dropsi-man the more he drinks the more he may, and by drinking he increaseth his thirst. Thus the Iewes by custome in sinning attaine to an height in wickednes▪ because euery act of offence hath his blot, and the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of acts offensiue, is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176348:12"/> increase of the blot or blemish of the soule till the light of nature be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguished, and men come to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate sense. This must be a warning to all men to take heede least they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any offēce against God in thought, word, or deede, considering euery of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence imprints a blot in the soule.</p>
            <p>Secondly it may be demanded, how Ierusalem growen to this height of Rebellion, can truly be called <hi>the holy Citie,</hi> or the <hi>Citie of the great king.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 27.53. and 5.35.</note> I answeare two waies. First, there were many holy men and women in Iurie and Ierusalem, that truly serued God and waited for the kingdome of Christ, as Ioseph, Marie, Zacharie, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, Anna, Simeon, Nichodemus, Ioseph of Aramathea, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Now a Church is named not of the greater but of the better part: as an heape of corne is so called, though there be more chaffe then corne. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly I answer that a people or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176348:13"/> Church that haue forsaken God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines still a reputed Church, till God forsake thē, as a wife cōmitting adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie remaines stil a supposed wife, til her husband giue her the bil of diuocemēt. Ierusalem indeede had forsaken God, but God had not forsaken Ierusalem. For there he preserued still the temple, and his worship: yea, when Ierusalem had condemned and crucified Christ, S. Peter inspired by the holy Ghost saith still,<note place="margin">Act. 2.39.</note>
               <hi>To you belong the promises, and to your children.</hi> And Ierusalem did not vtterly cease to be a Citie or Church of God, till they contradicted &amp; blasphemed the Apostolicall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery: for thē &amp; not before the Apostles withdrew thēselues frō the fellowship of the Iewes. Here we see a depth of mercie in God: for though the Iewes for their parts had deserued a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand thousand times to be forsaken, yet God for his part did not forsake them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176348:13"/> but still pursued thē with mercie. And we are taught hereby not to giue any sentēce of the persons of euill men. For though they forsake God, yet know we not, whether God haue forsaken them or no.</p>
            <p>In this example of Ierusalems Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, we learne many things. First in it we may he hold the vilenes of mans nature, and our violent pronesse to sinne. For the Iewes went about to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolish and quench as much as they could the doctrine of saluation; yea to quench it with blood, and which is more with the blood of the prophets: and this shewes that man drinkes ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, as the fish drinks in water.<note place="margin">Iob 15.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly in Ierusalem we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the desperate condition of the Church of Rome at this day. For it followes in Rebellion, nay it goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Ierusalem. If any man will indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently consider, it will appeare that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176348:14"/> by the whore of Babylon is meant the presēt church of Rome:<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.6.</note> &amp; this whore is said to be drunke with the blood of the Saints. The locusts out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomlesse pit goe to the kings of the earth to stirre thē vp to warre against the Church of God.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.14.</note> And these locusts are in all likelihoode, swarmes of monkes, fryers, &amp; Iesuits of the church of Rome. And we haue foūd it by long and much experience, that they of the Romane Church haue long thirsted for the bloode of prince and people in this land.</p>
            <p>Thirdly we are here taught to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise our selues in the duties of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, goodnesse, peace to all men. The prophet Isai saith that men in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Christ, shall not applie their swords and speares to the hurt of any, as the Iewes here doe, but shall turne them to instruments of husbandrie, as mattocks and sithes.<note place="margin">Isa. 2.4.</note> Whereby is sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176348:14"/> that men truly regenerate shall lay aside all purpose and minde of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any hurt, and shall giue themselues to doe the good they can. Againe he saith that the wolfe and the lambe shall dwell togither:<note place="margin">c. 11. v. 19.</note> and that there shall be no hurt in all the holy mount of God. The deuill by the sinne of our first pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, of men made vs beasts, lyons, wolfes, tygers, beares, cockatrices: and Christ again of beasts hath made vs his lambs and sheepe in respect of meeknes and patience.</p>
            <p>Fourthly we are here taught not to oppose our selues against the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of God, but without pride and fiercenes to yeeld subiection and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Ministerie.<note place="margin">Isa. 11.6.</note> Isai foretels that in the Church of the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a little childe, that is, Ministers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise weake and silly men, shall by their doctrine rule and guide wolfes, leopards, lyons, that is, fierce and cruell
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176348:15"/> men by nature. <hi>My people</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>shall come willingly in the day of assembly:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 110.3.</note> and <hi>the sheepe of Christ heare his voice and follow him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28.</note> The Iewes arraigne and iudge the prophets that are sent vnto them: but we must suffer them in their ministerie to arraigne and iudge vs, that we be not iudged of the Lord. Againe, the Iewes kill their teachers: but we must permit our tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers after a sort to kill vs: for their ministerie must be as it were a sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing knife to kill the old man in vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.16.</note> that we may be an acceptable offering vnto God.</p>
            <p>Lastly Ministers of the word, must learne hence not to be troubled, if they be hated and persequuted of men. For this befell the holy prophets of God and that in the citie of Ierusalem.</p>
            <p>The third point is the manner or forme of their Rebellion. In it I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foure things. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The will of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176348:15"/> which the Iewes rebell, <hi>I would:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the wil of the Iewes rebelling, <hi>ye would not:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the concord of both, <hi>I would, ye would not:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the manner of Gods will, He wills their saluation in loue, <hi>I would haue gathered you as an hen gathereth her chickens:</hi> in patience, <hi>How oft would I?</hi> Before I come to hādle these points in particular, I wil set downe a general preamble touching the nature of will.</p>
            <p>Will is a power of willing, nil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, choosing, refusing, suspending, which depends on reason. By <hi>power</hi> I meane an abilitie or created facultie: and it is so properly in men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: but in God onely by analogie or proportion. Because his will is his es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence or godhead indeede. Secondly, I say it is <hi>a power of willing,</hi> &amp;c. because to will, nill, choose, refuse, suspend, that is, neither to will nor to nill, are the proper effects of will whereby it is knowne and discerned. Lastly, I say <hi>it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176348:16"/> depends on reason,</hi> because it is incident onely to natures reasonable; as God, Angels, men: and because, though it goe against good reason, yet it is not without reason altogether. When a man knowes &amp; approoues that which is good, and yet doth the contrarie: it is because it seemes good to him to do the contrarie. And in euery act of will there are two things, <hi>Reason</hi> to guide, and <hi>Election</hi> to assent or dissent.</p>
            <p>Will hath his propertie, and that is the <hi>Libertie of the will,</hi> which is a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from compulsion, or constraint, but not from all necessitie. From com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsion; because compulsion and will be contrarie, and where compulsion takes place there will giues place, and will constrained is no will. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse will and necessitie may stand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. God wills many things of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute necessitie, as the eternall genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sonne, the proceeding of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176348:16"/> the Holy ghost, the doing of iustice and such like: and he wills them with most perfect libertie of will. The good angels will their owne hapines and the doing of iustice, and that of necessitie; for they cannot will to sinne or to be in miserie: and all this they will most freely. Nay the necessitie of not sinning is the glorie and ornament of will: for he that doth good so as he cannot sinn, is more at libertie in doing good, then he that can doe either good or euill. When the creature is in that estate that it willingly serues God &amp; cannot but serue God, then is our perfect li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. Againe, the libertie of will since the fall of man is ioyned with a necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of sinning, because it stands in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vnder sinne; in this respect it is fitly tearmed of Augustine,<note place="margin">Tract. in Ioh. 53. De corrept. &amp; grat. c. 13.</note>
               <hi>the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free will.</hi> Wherefore we may not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine in the will a Libertie which is a freedome from all necessitie. That
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176348:17"/> this may the better appeare, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the kinds of necessitie. There is a simple or <hi>absolute necessitie,</hi> when a thing cannot possibly be otherwise: thus we say there is a God, and he is righteous, &amp;c. This necessitie stands not with the will of the creature; yet doth it stand with Gods wil, in whom an absolute necessitie of holinesse and goodnes is ioyned with absolute free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of will. Againe there is a <hi>neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie by violence</hi> or compulsion, and this abolisheth freedome and consent of will. Thirdly there is a <hi>necessitie of infallibilitie,</hi> or of consequence, when some thing followes necessarily vpon a supposed antecedent, as namely vpon the determination and decree of God. This necessitie and freedō of will may both stand together.<note place="margin">Greg. Arim. l. 2 dist. 20. in fine▪ an sufficere ad rationē vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatii si à sciente &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntario com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittatur.</note> For to the doing of a voluntarie action it is sufficient, that it proceede of iudgement &amp; haue his beginning from within the will,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176348:17"/> though otherwise in respect of Gods will it be of vnchangeable necessitie. The certentie of Gods decree doth not abolish the consent of mans will, but rather order it and mildly incline or draw it forth. And the thing that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrarie to freedome of will is compulsion: because it abolisheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</p>
            <p>The libertie of will stands in a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power. The first is, when it wills a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, of it owne selfe to be apt and able to nill the same; and so on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie: and it is called in schooles the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of contradiction:</hi> the second is, when it wills any thing to be able to will an other thing or the contrarie. As for example: when God willed the creation of the world, he could haue nilled the same: and when he willed the creation of one world, he could haue willed the creatiō of mo worlds. And this latter is called the <hi>libertie of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176348:18"/> contrarietie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will by this libertie is distinguished frō the inclinations of natural Agents, which alwaies shew themselues in the same manner. Put matter to the fire, it burnes alwaies &amp; it can not but burne. Cast vp a stone into the aire, it fals down alwaies and can not but fall downe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly will by this libertie is distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed from the appetite of beasts: for it followes sense, and in choosing or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing keeps alwaies one order. The sheep flies the wolfe: and all sheep doe so at all times and in all places. Bees ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honie, and they doe so alwaies and in all places, and they can doe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise. When the beast in the field, chooseth one hearb, and refuseth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is a shewe of libertie, yet no true libertie. For that which it choseth or refuseth once, it choseth or refuseth alwaies in the same manner.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the generall nature of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176348:18"/> will: now I come to the points in hād. The first is touching the wil of Christ, <hi>I would.</hi> According to the two natures of Christ: so be there two wills in him, the will of his godhead and the will of his manhood. Some thinke that these words are ment of the will of his manhood. For they suppose him heere to speake as the minister of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and consequently as a man.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.8.</note> This I thinke is a truth, but not all the truth. Because the thing which he willeth namely the gathering of the Iewes by the ministerie of the Prophets, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and practised long before his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation. Wherefore (as I take it) here his divine will is ment or the will of his godhead, which is also the will of the Father, and the Holy Ghost.</p>
            <p>This will is one and the same as God is one: yet may it be distinguished on this manner.<note place="margin">Voluntas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne-placiti. Voluntas signi.</note> It is either <hi>the will of his good pleasure,</hi> or, <hi>his signifying
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176348:19"/> will.</hi> The truth of this distinction, wee may see in earthly Princes, who beare the image of God. A king determines within himselfe according to his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure what shalbe done in his kingdom, and what not: this is his will. Againe he signifies some part of his secret pleasure to his subiects, as occasion shall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred: and this is also his will. Euen so the pleasure of God within himselfe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e significations thereof to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures either in whole or in part, are bis will.</p>
            <p>The first is mentioned, Ephes. 1.5. where Paul saith the Ephesians <hi>were predestinate according to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his will.</hi> That it may be rightly conceiued of vs, I will set downe 4. things. The first is, that this will is Gods purpose or decree according to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell. For in it these two concurre, his counsell and his decree. His counsell sees all things and all the causes of them:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176348:19"/> His decree determines what shall be done and what vndone: and he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines according to his owne eternall counsell. Yet is not counsell a rule to his will. For there is nothing higher then his will, and his counsell also is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will which is goodnes it selfe. And therefore by Paul,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.11.</note> Counsell is called, <hi>the Counsell of his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly in Gods will there is a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie,</hi> that is an absolute power, whereby he is Lord of all the actions that hee willeth, willing of himselfe without dependance from any, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impediment or controlement, what he will, when he will, and how he will. Thus much is signified in the parable,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.</note>
               <hi>May I not doe with mine owne as I will:</hi> and by Paul alleadging Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>I will haue mercie on whome I will haue mercie;</hi> teaching also that we are at Gods pleasure, as clay at the pleasure of the potter. This must teach vs when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176348:20"/> we thinke or speake of Gods works &amp; iudgements, to thinke and speake in modestie and sobrietie, with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reverence, not dating to search in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reason of them, or think hardlie of them, when they sound not with our reason, contenting our selues with this that we know God to haue a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie in his will, to wil at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and his will to be good.</p>
            <p>The third point is, that the will of God is the beginning or first cause of all things without exception, and of all their motions and actions. And it is a beginning two waies. First in regard of the existence or being of things: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in regard of their goodnes. That all things in particular haue their Being from the wil of God as from the first efficient cause, I shew it thus. God is of that power, that nothing cā come to passe which he nilleth, or which is vtterly against his will. Therefore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176348:20"/> whatsoever comes to passe, comes to passe because he wils it either simply or in some part. A wise gouernour of a familie or of an armie, hauing all things in his owne power, suffers nothing to be done without his wil, and he desires in the very smallest matters to haue a stroke; and nothing hinders this desire but his owne weaknes, which is not incident to the maiestie of God. God by an vnchangeable presciēce foresees all things that shall come to passe: and therefore by an vnchangeable will he willeth the beeing of them. For Gods foreknowledge dependes on his will. Not because God foresees things to come, therefore they come to passe: but because according to Gods will they are to come to passe, therefore he foresees them. Indeede there is in God a knowledge of things that possibly may be, though they neuer be: and this knowledge goes before Gods decree.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176348:21"/> Yet the diuine knowledge of things that certenly shall be, followes the will and determination of God. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede further: In that God wills the beeing of all things, he makes them to be. For his will is operatiue, not seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from his power but distinguished: and his willing of any thing is his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: and therefore it pleaseth the Holy ghost to signifie the will of God by an operatiue word or commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>In the beginning God said, let there be this and that, and it was so:</hi> now this commanding word was his will. Againe, <hi>Man liues by euery word of God,</hi> that is, by any thing that God in his pleasure wills to be our foode. Things in respect of beeing must haue dependance on the will of God, or on themselues, or on some other thing. If they depend on themselues for their beeing, they are Gods: if they depend on any other thing without and beside
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176348:21"/> God, that thing is god also. It remaines therefore that all things and acts in the world considered as Acts, haue their beeing by a dependance on God as on the highest cause, or the cause of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. This doctrine must be remembred. For it is the foundation of true pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: when we consider, whatsoeuer comes to passe befalls vs according to the will of God.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Vpon this ground Iob armes himselfe to patience, and Dauid saith, <hi>I held my tongue &amp; said nothing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 39.9.</note>
               <hi>because thou Lord diddest it.</hi> Secondly this doctrine is the meanes of all true comfort, whē we consider that all our afflictions are from the good pleasure of God. Thus did the primitiue church comfort it selfe, when it considered, that the Iewes, Herod, Pontius Pilate, &amp; the rest, did nothing against Christ, <hi>but that which the counsell of God had determined before to be done</hi> And it must be out comfort,<note place="margin">Act. 4.28.</note> that we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinate
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176348:22"/> to be made conformable to the image of Christ in afflictions.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29. Phil. 3.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore the will of God is the beginning of the goodnes of things. For a thing is not first good and then willed by God: but it is first willed by God, and thus it becomes good. This is a manifest truth, I will not stand vpō it. It may here be demanded, whence the euill in the creature, namely sinne, hath his beginning. I answer: It comes of the will of the declining cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, and not from the will of God. Yet is it not without the will of God. For though he wil not sinne properly, because he hates it: yet doth he will the being of it in the world. For in respect of the counsell of God, it is good that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill should be. And God wills the being of sinne,<note n="a" place="margin">non positiuè.</note> not because it is his will to effect, produce, or giue a being to it, but because<note n="b" place="margin">negatiuè, deserendo.</note> his will is to forsake his creature, and not to hinder the being
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176348:22"/> of euill when he may: and<note n="c" place="margin">perillatione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thus euill not hindred comes to passe. And whereas God foresaw it in his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall counsell,<note place="margin">Hogu: Malum quod non vult. e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e vult.</note> and yet willed not to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it when he might, in effect he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the beeing of it in the worlde; though simply he wills it not.</p>
            <p>The last point is, that this will of Gods good pleasure being hiddē from vs, is not the rule of our actions and of our faith. Moses saith,<note place="margin">Deu. 29.29.</note>
               <hi>Secret things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Lord our God, and things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to vs and to our children.</hi> Hence it followes, that we doe and may (with a submission) in our wills dissent from this will of God before it is knowne to vs, without sinne. Paul would by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Apostolicall commission haue preached in Asia and Bythinia, and God would not, because it is said the spirit withstood him.<note place="margin">Act. 16.6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>▪</note> Yet did not Paul sinne herein. One good thing may differ from another: and that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176348:23"/> which the creature sometime willeth without offence, God willeth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise by his most righteous pleasure. Samuel prayes for Saul otherwise then the secret pleasure of God was;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but when the decree of God was reuealed to him, he then stayed his praying. Here sundry men are to be reprooued that reason thus. If it be the wil of God that I shal be saued, it shall so be, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer I liue: therefore I will liue as I list. They make the secret will of God the rule of their liues, which should not be: because the reuealed will of God is the Law, or the onely Rule of things to be done and beleeued.</p>
            <p>Thus we see what the will of Gods pleasure is. Now this wil is not ment in this text, <hi>How oft would I.</hi> For the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of god cānot be withstood or resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted. Isay. 46.10. <hi>My counsell shall stand, and I will do all my pleasure.</hi> But the wil here mentioned, may be resisted, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176348:23"/> withstood, <hi>I would, ye would not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The signifying will of God is, when he reuealeth some part and portion of his pleasure, so farre forth as it serues for the good of his creature, and for the manifestation of his iustice or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. This signifying will is not indeede the will of God properly, as the will of his good pleasure is, for it is the effect therof: yet may it truly be so tearmed. For as the effects of anger without the passion, are called anger in God: so the signe and signification of his will, may be tearmed will.</p>
            <p>This will is propounded sometimes more plainly, sometimes more darkly. It is propounded more plainely three waies, by his word, by his permission, by his operation.</p>
            <p>His word is his will, for so Paul saith,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note>
               <hi>Prooue what is the good wil of God</hi> And it is not his decree or pleasure, but his signifying will: because it serues to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176348:24"/> declare and manifest what is pleasing and acceptable to God, what is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and what he requires of vs, if we desire to come to life eternall. For this cause, both the Law and the Gospel and all the commandements, prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, promises and threatnings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are the signifying will of God. For commandements signifie what we are to doe: prohibitions what we are to leaue vndone: promises, what good he will doe vnto vs: threatnings, what punishments are due to sinne. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more by reasō of the word, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie and dispensation thereof is the signifying will of God. For by it God signifies his pleasure touching the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of men.</p>
            <p>Diuine permission is likewise the signifying will of God. For by it he sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, that he will not hinder the bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the thing permitted; and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that the thing permitted shall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176348:24"/> come to passe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly euery Operation or worke of God, signifies what God will haue done, and what must come to passe. For when a thing is done, we know thereby what is and was the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of God, considering nothing comes to passe without his will.</p>
            <p>When the signifying will is more darkly propounded, it is because some things appertaining to the said will, are concealed. And by reason of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealement, sometime there seemes to be a contrarietie betweene the signify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will and the will of his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: but indeede there is none. And the end, why God doth so darkly sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and propound his pleasure, is not to hurt or deceiue, but to procure the good of his creature. Examples of this kind, there be in Scripture three sorts. First of all, God sometimes propounds a commaundement to men and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceales
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176348:25"/> the end of the commandement. For the endes of diuine precepts are three: one is <hi>Obedience,</hi> when God wil haue the thing commanded, to be don precisely as it is commanded: the other is <hi>Triall,</hi> when he wills not the thing commanded to be done absolutely, but onely wills to make triall of the loialtie of his creature: the third is <hi>conuiction,</hi> when by commanding God intends to conuince his creature of disobedience. Thus parents sometime giue precepts to their children, that must be done: and sometime againe they giue a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, the doing whereof they intend not, but onely intend thereby to make experience of the affection and dutie of their children. And sometime one man commands an other onely in way of conuiction: as when the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour saith to the bankrupt, Pay thy debt: which he neuer lookes for, and which peraduenture he minds to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176348:25"/> Diuine precepts therefore be of three sorts, precepts of obedience, as the commandement of the moral law, precepts of triall, and precepts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction. Now when the signifying wil of God is propounded in a precept, &amp; the ende of the precept is concealed, the pleasure of God is darkly signified. God giues a commaundement to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, <hi>Offer thine onely sonne Isaac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.2.</note> The end was only to trie Abraham, &amp; this end was concealed, til Abrahā was in doing the fact, for then the angel of the Lord staied him &amp; said,<note place="margin">v. 12.</note> Now I see Abraham feares God. And the very commaudement, <hi>Offer Isaac,</hi> seemes to be flat contrarie to the will of Gods pleasure or decree: for, as it appeares by the euent, Isaac was not to be slaine: and therefore the not slaying of Isaac was decreed of God. Now then, it may be said, why should God command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing contrarie to his decree? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176348:26"/> there is an apparent cōtrariety, by reason the end of the commandement was concealed: but indeede there is none. For as it was the decree of God that Isaac should not be offered: so also was it his decree, that Abraham should be tried in the offering of Isaac. And with this decree doth this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accord. For it is a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not so much of absolute obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as of triall, and therefore it is a fit and conuenient meanes to accomplish the decree of God. The Lord by the hand of Moses giues a commādement to Pharao,<note place="margin">Exod. 8.1.</note>
               <hi>Let the people goe:</hi> and yet the secret pleasure &amp; purpose of God was, that he should not let them goe. Here is contrarietie in shew, but indeed none. For it was also the decree of god, to conuince Pharao of rebellion and hardnes of heart: and to this end serues this commandement: because properly according to Gods intention it was a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176348:26"/> commandement of cōuiction: though Pharao for his part was to accept of it as of a commandement to be obeied and accomplished.</p>
            <p>By this doctrine the publike mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of the word receiues a iust de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Some are of opiniō, it is a meanes to delude the world: because in it a commandement is giuen to all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception to repent and beleeue, and yet grace to repent and beleeue is not. But they are deceiued. For the commandement, <hi>Repent, and beleeue,</hi> though in the intent of the minister it haue onely one end, namely the saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all, yet in the intention and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of God, it hath diuers ends. In them which be ordained to life eternall, it is a precept of obedience: because God will inable them to do that which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth: in the rest it is a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of triall or conviction, that to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers their sinne might be discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176348:27"/> and all excuse cut off. Thus when the precept is giuen to beleeue and not the grace of faith, God doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude, but reprooue and convince men of vnbeleefe and that in his iustice.</p>
            <p>The second example of the signify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will of God darkly propounded is, when God propoundes his promises concealing the exception or condition thereof. Gen. 1.28. <hi>Ye shall rule ouer the fowles of the aire, the fishes of the sea, &amp; the beasts of the earth.</hi> And of Hierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem the Lord saith, Psal. 132.14. <hi>This is my rest for euermore.</hi> These promises take no place now: and yet there is no contrarietie in Gods will, because the said promises must be vnderstood with their exception; vnlesse ye fall from me and prouoke mine anger by your sinnes.</p>
            <p>The third example is, when God propoundes his threats concealing the conditions and exceptions thereof. Iud.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176348:27"/> 10.13. <hi>I will,</hi> saith the Lord, <hi>deliuer you no more.</hi> And it was his pleasure after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to deliuer them againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Exod. 32.10. <hi>Let me alone, that my wrath may waxe hote: for I vvill consume them:</hi> and he spared them at the praier of Moses. Ion. 3.4. <hi>Yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie daies and Niniuie shall be destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> For all this Niniuie was spared and not destroyed. We may not here so much as dreame of any chaunge or vntruth in God. For all threatnings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, must be vnderstood with this clause,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.21.</note>
               <hi>Except ye repent and turne vnto me.</hi> And this exception God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceales, that he may the better terrifie the consciences of men and so prepare them to true repentance. Isay. 38.1. the Lord saith by the Prophet to Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t thine house in order, for thou shalt die and not liue:</hi> and yet he liued fifteene yeares after. Here God conceals his owne pleasure of lengthning the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176348:28"/> daies of Ezechias, and signifies, what shall betide him in respect of nature &amp; the helps thereof. In all these examples we may not surmise any fraud or dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing in God. For he doth not speak one thing and minde another, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fashion of hypocrites: but he conceals part of his will and reueals part: and this he doth not for the hurt of any after the manner of deceiuers, but for the good of men.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the signifying will of God: now I come to the text in hand. The words, <hi>I would haue gathered you,</hi> are not to be vnderstood of the decree of God, but of this signifying will and namely of the ministerie of the word. For when God sent his word to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem by his Prophets, he therby sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified that it was his pleasure and will to gather and conuert them. And he is said to wil the conversion of the Iewes in and by his word two wayes. First
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176348:28"/> because he approoued it as a good thing in it selfe, being agreeable to his goodnes and mercie. Secondly because he commaunded and required it of them as a dutie of theirs, and as a thing necessarie to saluation. Some may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily say, it is a point of hard dealing, for God to commaund the Iewes to doe that which they can not doe, and to complaine because they are not gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and that a maister might aswell commaund his seruant to carrie a mountaine on his back, and complaine because it is not done. I aunswer thus: If a maister could giue to his seruant power and abilitie to carrie a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, he might then commaund him to do it: and if he should by his owne default loose this abilitie, the said mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster might still commaund him and complaine, if he did not the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. And this is the case with God. For he gaue all men grace in our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176348:29"/> first parents to obey any of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements: this grace in them we haue cast away, &amp; do not of our selues so much as desire it of God: and God for his part is not bound to giue vs this grace againe. He therefore may iustly commād vs to turne vnto him, though we now be vnable to turne.</p>
            <p>If we compare this text with Isa. 6.10. they may seeme to be contrarie. For here Christ saith, <hi>I would haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered you:</hi> there he saith, <hi>Harden them that they be not gathered and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> God therefore seemes to will and not to will one and the same thing. <hi>Answ.</hi> There is but one will in God: yet doth it not equally wil all things, but in diuers respects it doth will and nill the same thing. He wills the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion of Hierusalem, in that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooues it as a good thing in it selfe: in that he commands it, and exhorts men to it: in that he giues them all outward
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176348:29"/> meanes of their conuersion. He wills it not, in that he did not decree effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worke their conuersion. For God doth approoue, and he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire many things, which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse for iust causes knowne to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, he will not doe. The confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Angels that fell, God approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as a thing good in it selfe, yet did not he will to confirme them. A iudge in compassion approoues and wills the life of a malefactour: and yet withall he wills the exequution of iustice in his death. Euen so God sometime wills that in his signifying will, which he wills not in the will of his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
            <p>By this which hath bin said, we learn, that where God erects the ministerie of his word, he signifies thereby that his pleasure is to gather men to saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In this regard the prophet Isay saith, that the preaching of the gospel, is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176348:30"/>
               <hi>a banner displayed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 49.22.</note> that all nations may come vnto it. All this is verified in this our English nation. For more then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares hath God displayed this ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vnto vs, and more then fortie years hath he signified in the ministerie of his word, that his will is to giue mercie &amp; saluation vnto vs. First therefore we owe vnto God all thankfulnes &amp; praise for this endles mercie. Secondly we are to reuerence the ministerie of the word, in as much as God signifies his good will vnto vs therby, &amp; we are in all obedience to subiect our selues to it: and for this cause we must suffer our selues to be conuerted and gathered by it. Subiects vse to reuerence the letter of their Prince, how much more then must we reuerence the letter of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God sent vnto vs, that is, the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of the word, &amp; cōform our selues to it. thirdly, hēce we may learn to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>see our miserable condition in this lād.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176348:30"/> For though God for his part haue long signified his will vnto vs touching our euerlasting good, yet there is nothing to be found in the most of vs, but a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect or contempt of the gospell: and in most places men are wearie of it as the Israelites were of Māna. What weary of the goodnes of God, that offers and proclaimes mercie vnto vs? Yea, vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And the more wearie we are of this, the more wearie are we of our owne happines, and consequently ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten to our owne perdition.</p>
            <p>Secondly it is to be obserued, that the rebellion of Ierusalem is against the signifying will of Christ, whē he saith, <hi>I would, ye would not.</hi> And hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that the signifying will of God is the rule of our obedience and not the vnreuealed wil. And threfore so oft as God signifies vnto vs his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, we must yeeld our selues in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it. Now God signifies his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176348:31"/> will three waies (as I haue said) by his commaundements and prohibitions, by his permission and by his operatiō. Therefore when be commaunds, we must obey: when he forbids, we must also obey. When he permits any euil, we must be content. Lastly when God doth any thing &amp; brings it to passe, he signifies his pleasure, and we must o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. We are bidden to say, <hi>Thy will be done:</hi> and this is not onely the will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in his word but also his will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed by any euent. For when any thing comes to passe, it comes to passe because it was the wil of God. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more this signifying will must be the stay and ground of our patience and comfort. For when a thing is come to passe, the will of God is past vpon it &amp; he hath signified his pleasure: As for example, when a man is slaine, the will of God is past vpon his life, and he hath reuealed his pleasure touching his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176348:31"/> death. Vpon this consideration in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents, are we to stay our mindes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it appeares hence, what minde must be in the Ministers &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the word. They must put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all blinde respects of profit and praise, and simply with honest hearts applie themselues and their Ministerie to this end, that they may gather a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to God. For that which is the mind of the master in any busines, the same must also be the minde of the seruant: the minde of the master is here set downe, <hi>How oft would I haue gathered you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of the will of God: now let vs come to the second point, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what is the will of man. That this may appeare, two things must be hādled, the <hi>Nature</hi> of mans will,<note place="margin">1. Natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. Vires.</note> &amp; <hi>the strength</hi> therof. Of the <hi>nature</hi> of will, I spake somthing before generally, there is yet somewhat more to be added.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176348:32"/> The nature of mans will, may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the practise thereof. The practise of will stands in fiue things. The first is the action of the minde, nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly a Cōsideration of the thing to be done, and the ende thereof: the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is <hi>Deliberation</hi> of the diuerse meanes, whereby the foresaide thing may be done: the third is, after delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration a <hi>Determination</hi> what shall be done. The fourth action is proper to the will, and that is <hi>Election,</hi> whereby the will vpon determination of the minde, chooseth or refuseth, that is, willeth what shall be done, what not. The fifth is, that the will in all her Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions keepes and maintaines <hi>her liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> Because when it wills or nills any thing, it mooues it selfe freely of it selfe to will or to nill, without any externall compulsion: &amp; when it wils any thing, it so wills, as stil retaining a natural apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to nill the same: and when it wills
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176348:32"/> any one particular thing, it remaines still apt not to will it, but to will an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing or the contrarie.</p>
            <p>Againe the will of man must be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished from the <hi>power</hi> of man, whereby he doth any thing. Will and power in God are onely distinguished in our conceiuing, beeing indeede one and the same thing, namely the essence of God. And therefore, what God can will, he can doe: what he willeth he doth: and his willing of any thing is his doing of it. It is not so in man, who can will that which he can not doe: as Paul saith, <hi>To will is present with me, but I can not doe that which I vvould.</hi> Will therefore is one thing, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe the thing willed, an other.</p>
            <p>The second thing to be handled, is <hi>the strength</hi> of will, that is, what will can doe, what not; and how farre it extends it selfe. That this may appeare, Will must be considered according to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176348:33"/> the foure estates of man, the estate of innocencie before the fall, the estate of corruption after the fall, the estate of regeneration after conuersion, and the estate of glorie after this life.</p>
            <p>In the estate of Innocencie, the will of man is a power of willing either good or euill. For God gaue Adam a commaundement, in which he forbad him to eate of the tree of knowledge of good &amp; euill. Adam therefore could either keep or break this commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This reason holds not in vs since the fall, yet doth it hold in Adam. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause with the commaundement he receiued the power to obey: and that he could not obey, it appeared by the euent; because he did not obey. Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astes saith,<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.19.</note>
               <hi>God made man righteous:</hi> there is the power to will that which is good: <hi>&amp; they found out many inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> there is also a power to will that which is euill. Moses saith to the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176348:33"/>
               <hi>I set before you this day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 30.19.</note>
               <hi>life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose life, that thou and thy seed may liue.</hi> These words are a sentence of the law, telling what we ought to do, and not what we can now do, but what we could do by the gift of creation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fall. Here a differēce of powers must be made: the power to will that which is good, was a gift put into A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams heart by God: and the power to will that which is euill, was in him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fall not a gift but onely a <hi>Possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to will euill,</hi> if he should cease to do his dutie. And thus had he power to will both good and euill.</p>
            <p>In Adams will there were two things, <hi>Libertie</hi> and <hi>Mutabilitie.</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie was twofould. The first is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie simply to wil, or to nill, or to sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. And this is <hi>libertie of nature:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is founded in the nature of will, from which it can not possiblie be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176348:34"/> and therefore it still remaines in the damned spirits: because where this libertie is wanting, there is no will.</p>
            <p>The second libertie is a <hi>libertie of grace,</hi> which is a power to will or nill well, or to will that which is good, and to nill that which is euill. This libertie is founded not in the nature but in the goodnes of the will. By goodnes I meane the holines of the will, which is the image of God. And here we must take heed of the opinion of some, who think that Adam was created and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in such a condition, in which he was neither righteous not vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but in a meane betweene both. But this is directly contrarie to the Apostle who saith, that mā was created in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes &amp; holines.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.24. Col. 3.10.</note> And by this meanes in the first instant of Adams creation, he wanted libertie of grace. Againe by reason of this second libertie, Adam had a further libertie from sinne and a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176348:34"/> libertie from miserie.</p>
            <p>The changeablenes of Adams will appears in this, that though it was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in goodnes, yet was it made chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geably good. For such was the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and inclination of his will to obey God, as might be altered and changed by force of temptation. The cause of this mutabilitie must be considered, &amp; it is this. That a creature righteous by creation may remaine eternal and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly righteous, two fauours or helps of God are required: the<note n="a" place="margin">1. posse vell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. perseuerare. Aug. de Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rep. &amp; gr. c. 11. 12.</note> first is a Power to perseuere in goodnesse. Without this power the creature of it self ceaseth to be good. The<note n="b" place="margin">2. Actus pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerandi.</note> secōd is an Act or deed, and that is the will to perseuere, or perseuerance it selfe. This also is required with the former, for God giues not onely the power but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the will and the deed. And the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not the good which it can do, vnlesse God cause it to do the said
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176348:35"/> good, as he caused it to be able to doe good. Both these helps the good angels haue, and therefore they stand. And as for Adam, he receiued of God the first helpe and not the second. For beside the goodnes of his will he receiued of God a power constantly to perseuere in goodnes if he would: yet the acte of perseuerance was left to the choise and libertie of his owne will. We may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the like in nature. God creates the eye and puts into it the facultie of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and withall he addes to the eye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie helpe by the light of the sunne: as for the act of seeing, it is left to mans libertie: for he may see if he will; and againe if he will, he may shut his eyes. The physitian by art procures an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; this done, in the next place he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides cōuenient food: yet the act of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is in the pleasure of the patiēt. For he may eat if he wil, &amp; if he will not he may abstaine. And thus God gaue Adā
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176348:35"/> the power to perseuere in righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but the will he left to himselfe.</p>
            <p>It may be saide, if Adam receiued power to doe good if he would, and not the will to will that he could, he then receiued not sufficient grace. I answer: he receiued sufficient for the perfection of his nature, for the full o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the wil of God, and for the attainment of euerlasting happines, if he would not be wanting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: but he receiued not sufficient grace for the causing of the immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of his nature: neither was it of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie to be giuen to a creature. A goldsmith intends to make a iewell of greatest value &amp; price: he compounds it of gold, pearle &amp; pretious stones: whē he hath brought it to perfection, he doth not put this condition to it, that if it fall it shall not be bruised or broken. And God created Adam in all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and gaue him a power and abilitie
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176348:36"/> to continue in the said perfection if he would: yet did not he put vnto his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture this condition, that it should be vnchangeable and vnalterable, when it should be assailed by the force of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward temptation.</p>
            <p>The vse of the former doctrine. In Adams example, we see the weaknes of the excellentest creature in it selfe without the grace of God. For Adam hauing power to perseuere, could not for all this, acte or put in exequution the saide power without the further helpe of God. He could fall of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, he could not stand or rise againe: he could not auoide the least euill, but as he was helped by God. We therefore beeing sinnefull wretches, much more are to acknowledge our infirmitie, and to ascribe all we doe or can doe that is good to the grace of God. Thus haue the godly alwaies done.<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 31.18.</note> The Iewes in their repentance say, <hi>Conuert thou me, and I will conuert.</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:176348:36"/> The spouse of Christ saith,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note>
               <hi>Draw vs and we will runne after thee.</hi> Dauid saith, <hi>Incline my heart to thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, turne mine eyes from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of vanitie, and quicken me in thy precepts.</hi> Augustine said, <hi>Giue that which thou commandest, and command what thou wilt.</hi> We are to God as the sicke man to his keeper, who saith, Take me vp and I will rise: hold me and I will stand. In regard of this our frailtie, it is the best for vs to denie our selues, and by faith to depende on the prouidence and mercie of God.</p>
            <p>Againe such as beleeue in Christ haue great cause to be thākfull to God. For they haue the beginnings of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace then euer Adam receiued. He receiued onely the power to perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in his happie estate,<note place="margin">Aug. de Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rep. &amp; grat. c. 11.</note> if he himselfe would: but they that beleeue beside the power of perseuerance, receiue the wil and the deed. Paul saith, work your saluation with feare and trembling: and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176348:37"/> then he adds,<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 2.13.</note>
               <hi>It is God that works in vs the will and the deed,</hi> whereby we run the race to eternall life.</p>
            <p>In the estate of corruption, two things are to be considered of mans will, the first what it can do, and how neere it comes to the doing of a good work. The second, what it can not do. For the declaration of the first, two things must br considered in corrupt will, a libertie and a possibilitie. The <hi>libertie</hi> is a certen freedome to will or nill, or to suspend. For this libertie is remaining since the fal of Adam, and is naturall to the will, from which it can not possibly be seuered. This libertie is large and sheweth it selfe in three kind of actions, <hi>naturall, humane, ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</hi> Naturall actions are such as are common to men and beasts, as to eate, drink, sleep, smel, heare, taste, mooue▪ common experience declares a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of will in all these actions.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:176348:37"/>
            <p>Humane actions are such as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all men: and I may fitly reduce them to three heads. The first is, the studie and practise of arts, trades, occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations and professions of all kindes. And that man hath freedome of will in all these, experience testifieth. The second is, the gouernment of societies, namely of families and cōmon-welths. The Lord said to Cain of Abel,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note>
               <hi>his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite shall be subiect to thee,</hi> that is, in freedome of thy will thou shalt rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, and his will shall be subiect to thine. Peter said to Ananias, that, the giuing or the not giuing of his lands was before he gaue them,<note place="margin">Act. 5.4.</note> in his owne libertie. And Paul saith, that the father <hi>hath the power of his owne will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to giue or not to giue his child in mariage, as he shall see occasion. The third is the practise of ciuill vertue, iustice, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, liberalitie, chastitie. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Paul saith, that the Gentiles <hi>do the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176348:38"/> thing contained in the law,</hi> and <hi>that by nature.</hi> For outwardly to be chast, iust, bountifull and so forth, is in the power of naturall and corrupt will. It may be said, that these things are the gift of the Holy ghost. I answere thus: the gifts of the Holy ghost are two fold, <hi>gifts of restraint,</hi> and <hi>gifts of renouation.</hi> Gifts of restraint are such as serue onely to keep in the corruption of nature and not to mortifie or abolish it. And they are common to all men both good &amp; bad, and serue onely to maintaine out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and comely order in the societies of men. Of this kinde are ciuil vertues. Gifts of renovation, are such graces of the Holy ghost, as serue not onely to restraine the corruption of the inward man, but also to mortifie it in the root and to make a change of our sinfull nature. Now vertues of this kinde, are onely incident to such as are in Christ.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:176348:38"/>
            <p>The third kind of actions are Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall, namely such as pertaine to the outward duties of the worship of god. And there is also a Libertie of will in them. For corrupt and sinnefull man, hath power and libertie to thinke of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and to thinke many things of him, good in themselues:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.14.</note> power to read and search the Scriptures:<note place="margin">Psal. 50.16.</note> power to speake and talke of the word of God: power to come to the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and heare a sermon,<note place="margin">Act. 17.20.</note> as the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did: power to conceiue a zeale (I say not a good zeale, but onely a zeale I say) for the maintenance of outward duties of religion. Paul saith, that the obstinate Iewes had a zeale of God, and were followers of the iustice of the Law;<note place="margin">Rom. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and 9.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Phil. 3.6.</note> and that himselfe beeing a phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie vnconuerted, was vnreprooueable in respect of the Law of God. Thus farre can man proceede by the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of corrupt will: and the deuill
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176348:39"/> by naturall strength goes somewhat further.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> For he is saide to beleeue▪ and he conceiues his faith not by illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the spirit of God, as man doth; but by the remainders of the light of nature, and by the power which yet remaines in his corrupted will. For we may not supppose that since his fall, he is inlightned by the spirit of God in any thing.</p>
            <p>Thus we see what is the libertie of corrupt will. We must yet further conceiue it to be full of weaknes and imbecillitie, which I will expresse in three rules.</p>
            <p>The first: <hi>that which the will can wil, it can not do, vnlesse God wil.</hi> Herupon S. Iames bids vs say, we will do this or that,<note place="margin">Iam. 4, 15.</note> if God will. And Paul wishing that he might haue a prosperous iourney to Rome,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.32.</note> adds this clause, <hi>By the will of God.</hi> Herode,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Pontius Pilate and the Iewes did nothing against Christ but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176348:39"/> that which the counsell of God had determined before to be done.</p>
            <p>The second: <hi>That which the vvill can will, it cannot do without the helpe of God:</hi> for in him we liue, mooue, and haue our beeing. This helpe is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, <hi>Preseruation</hi> of the will both for power and acte, and the <hi>Direction</hi> thereof, whereby it is ordered and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the things it willeth.</p>
            <p>The third: <hi>Often the will neither willeth nor doth the things it can will and doe, because it is hindred.</hi> It is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered sometimes by the minde that misleades the will: sometimes again by the worke of Satan. Thus Paul saith, <hi>that satan hindred him from comming</hi> to Thessalonica.</p>
            <p>The vse of this doctrine is twofold. First the libertie of the will is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the world. For in ciuill and Ecclesiasticall actions men doe not that which they can doe: so farre be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176348:40"/> the most from doing that which the Gospel requires, that they doe not that which nature can doe. Some plead, that if they be ordained to saluation, they shall certenly be saued, otherwise not: and therefore they say they will leaue all to God, and liue as they list: but this shall be their condemnation, that they haue not liued according to ciuill vertue as they might, they come not to the Church, they search not the Scriptures, they heare not sermons: in a word, they vse not the good meanes of saluation so farre as they are able to vse them by the strength of nature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the weaknesse of will in his libertie must teach vs to abate our pride, and to humble our selues: because we can not doe any thing, no not so much as mooue hand, foote, or fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger without the helpe of God.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. king. 13.4.</note> Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boā, whē he had stretched out his hand to lay hold on the prophet, could not
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176348:40"/> so much as pull it in againe. And this consideration must likewise mooue vs to be thankfull to God, because the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions we doe, we doe by him.</p>
            <p>The second thing to be considered in the corrupt will, is<note n="c" place="margin">Possibilitas non activa so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> passiva, vel po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia materiae,</note>
               <hi>a Possibilitie</hi> of willing that which is good. This possibilitie is a certaine condition of the wil, whereby it can wil that which is good, after that God hath preuented vs with his grace. A stone is not of this nature, neither is the beast, because they are creatures vnreasonable, wanting both will and vnderstanding: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no way capable of grace: whereas man in that he hath will and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, hath a possibilitie of doing that which he cannot doe. The fathers in this sense say, <hi>To be able to haue faith is nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de praed▪ sanct. c. 5.</note>
               <hi>to haue faith indeede is grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto I haue shewed what will can doe in the corrupt estate of man:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176348:41"/> now let vs see what it cannot doe. And because here the maine differences come to be considered, betweene vs and the Church of Rome; I will first lay downe a sure ground and then build vpon it. The ground is this: <q>Though libertie of nature remaine, yet libertie of grace, that is, libertie to will vvell is lost, extinguished, abolished by the fall of Adam.</q> I prooue it thus. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of grace is founded in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or integritie of the will: now this goodnes of the will is abolished by the fall of Adam: and therefore the libertie it selfe that is sounded thereon. That the goodnes or integritie of the will is lost, I confirme it thus. That which we put on in our conuersion, we want by nature: we put on this goodnes in our conuersion. For in it we <hi>put on the new man created according to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God in iustice and holines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as Paul saith. Againe if all the motions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:176348:41"/> and inclinations of the heart be euill, and onely euill, and continually euill, there is no goodnes in the heart: but the first is true. For the Lord saith, that he <hi>saw the frame of the thoughts of the heart to be onely euill continually.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> Paul makes three parts of man in the estate of Innocencie, the <hi>bodie,</hi> the <hi>soule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Thess. 5.23.</note> and the <hi>spirit,</hi> that is, the image of God wrought by the spirit, beeing the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and glorie of both the former. Now since the fall, the spirit is turned to flesh:<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.3.6.</note> for <hi>what soeuer is borne of flesh is flesh</hi> (saith Christ,) that is, wholly flesh and onely flesh: and the naturall dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of the flesh is to lust against the spirit. What goodnes then can be in the will. He that must enter into the kingdom of heauen must first be <hi>borne againe:</hi> now looke as it is in the first birth, so is it in the second. In the first, an imperfect man is not made a perfect man, but that which is no man is made
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176348:42"/> a man: euen so in the second birth, he that is a sinner &amp; hath nothing in him to please God, is made iust and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. For regeneration is not in respect of the substance of bodie or soule, nor in respect of the faculties of the soule, but onely in respect of the goodnesse thereof, which is a conformitie to the will of God. And if there be any part or portion thereof yet remaining, there cannot be a new birth, but onely a repairing of that which is decaied, with a confirmation and increase of it.</p>
            <p>The second reason. There is<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vnderstand that which is called in schools</hi> potentia activa, <hi>or,</hi> potentia for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, <hi>which we say is lost: the Papists say no.</hi> Intelligi non potest o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ad opera pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatis activè vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas humana concurrat, si non habeat ex se po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam activam saltem remotam. <hi>Rursus,</hi> habet po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam remotam &amp; vires imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas. <hi>Bellarm. de grat. &amp; lib. arbit. l. 6. c. 15.</hi>
               </note> no power or aptnes in the will corrupted to will that which is truly good. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore libertie of grace to wil well is lost. The minor I prooue thus. Ezech. 36.26. <hi>A new heart also will I giue you, and a new spirit will I put within you, and I will take away the stonie heart out of your bodie, and I will giue you an
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:176348:42"/> heart of flesh.</hi> Here two things are set down distinctly. The first, that the new &amp; fleshie heart is the gift of god, that is, an heart readie and apt to giue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The second, that there is in vs no aptnes or abilitie to receiue this gift of God: because our hearts are stonie. God therefore giues the fleshie heart, and the aptnes to receiue this gift by taking away the stonie heart. Christ saith, that none can come vnto him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.44.</note> vnlesse the father <hi>Draw him.</hi> Now if there were in vs by nature the least power or aptnes to come to Christ, then drawing were needlesse, (for that argues obstinate rebellion) and it were sufficient to succour, helpe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the foresaid power, without any more adoe. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that the <hi>wisdome of the flesh,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> the best in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and motions of the minde of a natural mā, are not only enemies, but euen <hi>enmitie to God.</hi> Now in enmitie,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:176348:43"/> there is nothing but hatred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God. And in the hatred of God, what inclination or aptnes can there be to loue and obey him? Againe <hi>Paul</hi> saith, The naturall man is <hi>not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the things of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note>
               <hi>for they are foolishnes to him: neither can be know them, for they are spiritually discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> In the minde of a naturall man there be two things to be considered, the act and the power of knowing &amp; approouing that which is truly good. And here <hi>Paul</hi> giues his sentence of both: of the act, that the minde cannot know the things of God: of the power, that the minde hath no capablenes or aptnes to acknowledge or approoue them;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as a little vessel hath no aptnes to receiue a great quantitie of liquour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.</note> we are not <hi>apt or sufficient of our selues</hi> to thinke a good thought as of our selues, but our sufficiencie is of God. Therefore nature corrupted
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176348:43"/> wants abilitie so much as to thinke a good thought: much lesse to will that which is good. Againe Paul tells the Ephesians that they <hi>vvere dead in sinnes and trespasses.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And this death or deadnesse is not onely in respect of the performance of that which is good, but also in regard of power to performe it. For if the least power to do good remaine since the fal, man is not dead as yet,<note place="margin">ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but dying or drawing on: because as yet some porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of spirituall life remaines. And if this be so: how are we quickned together with Christ: and how is it a wonder, <hi>that the dead heare the voyce of Christ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.25.</note> Againe, Paul saith to the Ephesians that they were <hi>once darknes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but now are light in the Lord. Now in darknes there is no aptnes at all either to giue or to receiue light. But how were they made light?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note> without any work or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operation of theirs: euen as in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176348:44"/> light was taken not from some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther precedent beginnings of light, but out of darknes, which conferred no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all to the beeing of light.</p>
            <p>The third reason: There is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Impotencie to good, but such a forcible pronesse and disposition to euill, as that we can do nothing but sinne.<note place="margin">Ier. 27.9.</note> Ieremie saith, <hi>that the heart of man is wicked aboue all things, who can know it.</hi> Paul saith that the Romanes were once <hi>seruants of sinne</hi> &amp; <hi>free in respect of righteousnes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.20.</note> and of himself, that the law was spirituall, <hi>he carnall &amp; sold vnder sinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 7.</note> And of vnrepentant sinners he saith, that they are <hi>in the snare of the deuill according to his will.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.26.</note> And this disposition of which I speak, is not to some few sinnes, but to al sinns without exception: because, as euery man takes of Adam the whole nature of man, euen so he takes the whole corruption of mans nature. And where
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176348:44"/> this huge &amp; horrible masse of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō takes place, there all inclination and power to goodnes must needes giue place. It may be obiected, that if the wil be in bondage, vnder sin, it hath lost his libertie quite. <hi>I answer;</hi> not so: for both may stand together. The prisoner though he haue lost a great part of his libertie, yet hath he not lost al: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the prison he may (as he will) either sitt, stand, lie or walk. And though he which is captiue to sin can do nothing but sinne, yet may he in sinning vse his libertie: and in the diuers kinds of euils intended, shew the freedome of his will.</p>
            <p>The fourth reason. All the goodnes we haue and all we can do that is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to God, is wholly in Scripture as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to God. He that is the child of God, is born of God: <hi>not of blood,</hi> that is, not of naturall generatiō:<note place="margin">Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>not of the will of the flesh,</hi> that is, not of the power and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:176348:45"/> inclination of naturall will, <hi>not of the will of man,</hi> that is, the heroicall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of excellent men. We are the workmāship of God created in Christ to good works.<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> Now the creature confers nothing to his creation, which is wholly from the Creator: because to create is not to make something of something but something of nothing. Christ saith without me ye can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And the reason is there rendred. Because Christ is the vine, and they which beleeue are vine brāches: which branches, that they may bring forth good fruit, must first be set into Christ, and then draw their sap, that is power to do good, from him.</p>
            <p>Patrons of nature against the grace of God, alleadge foure speciall reasons for liberty of wil in moral acts, that is, in things and actions good according to the morall law. <hi>The first is</hi> this. God hath giuen sundry commandements
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176348:45"/> to man since his fall, some pertaining to the law, some to the gospel, as commā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements to turne vnto God, to beleeue, to repent. And all commandements are giuen in vain, vnlesse there be free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of will to do them or not to doe them. <hi>I answer</hi> first, these commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments set not downe what we can do, but what we should do: they signifie not our abilitie but our office and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whereby we should please God &amp; come to saluation. And if the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements be impossible, it is not Gods fault but ours: for they are not impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to created but to corrupted nature. Secondly, though we can not wil to do that which God commands; yet are not his commandements idle. For they are the instruments and meanes of the spirit of God, whereby he effects in vs the good he commands.</p>
            <p>The <hi>second obiection.</hi> We are boūd to giue vnto God an account of all our
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176348:46"/> doings in the day of iudgement, and this were not equall vnlesse we had power to will both good and euill. <hi>I aunswer,</hi> It sufficeth to binde vs to a reckning, that once we had libertie in Adam to will either good or euil. And all men since the fal haue some measure of libertie of will: the wicked libertie in sinne: the righteous libertie in duties of righteousnes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third obiection</hi> from testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture. It is alleadged that the Samaritane,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.</note> which lay wounded betweene Ierico &amp; Ierusalē is a figure of mākind halfe dead in sinn. <hi>I answer,</hi> that in parables nothing may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered that is beside the scope thereof: and the scope of this parable is nothing els, but to shew who is our neighbour. Againe, we graunt that libertie of wil is not abolished but wounded. Because, though libertie of grace to will wel be lost, yet libertie of nature to wil, stil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176348:46"/> Againe the words of Christ to the angell of Laodicea, are obiected. <hi>Behold I stand at the dore and knock: if any man open I will come in.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.20.</note> Here (say some) to knock is the work of grace, and to open the work of free-will. <hi>I answer,</hi> that the words, (if any man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen) are conditionall: and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine nothing of the power of will either to or fro. Againe, the words set not downe what the angell is able to do, but what his office is and what he can doe by grace. Furthermore the place of Deuteronomie is obiected. <hi>The word which I commaund thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 30.14.</note>
               <hi>is neere thee that thou mayst do it.</hi> But in these words Moses sets downe, what the Israelites can do by the grace of a Mediatour, who fulfilling the law for vs, and giuing grace to obey the same; makes the commandements of the law (which otherwise are impossible) to be easie. Thus Paul hath expounded
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176348:47"/> this text Rom. 10.8. where he signifies, that sentences of the law must not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally but euangelically be vnderstood of them that are in Christ, and fulfil the law by him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth obiection.</hi> When man is conuerted, he is not conuerted against his wil: for then God should deale with a man after the manner of a stone or a beast. Therefore he which is conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is conuerted with the consent of his owne will. <hi>Answer.</hi> This consent is not of our selues but of God. For as the conuersion is of God, so is the wil to be conuerted. Of this point, more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Vpon the ground formerly deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, sundry questions of great moment are resolued. The first is, whether a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man or an infidel, can by the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his will, without faith and without the helpe of God, doe any worke morally good, that is, a worke
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:176348:47"/> in which there is no sinne. They of the Church<note n="a" place="margin">Alex. 3. para. Summa q. 66. Thom▪ in 1.2. q. 109. Bon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. in 2. Sent. d. 28. Bellar. de gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; lib. arb. l. 5. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of Rome for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares haue answered, yea: for they confidently teach, <hi>that a man pressed with no temptation, may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, by the speciall helpe of God, and without it, by his owne strength so doe that which is morally good, that no sinne at all be committed therein.</hi> We answer, no: and that vpon sufficient warrant. For such as the beginning of an action is, such is the action it selfe. Now the minde and will of man are the beginnings of all their actions: and in them there is no abilitie to thinke or to will that which is truly good, but a continuall disposition to the contrarie. All actions therefore proceeding thēce are onely and continually euill. Vpon this ground <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>that to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,</hi> the vse of <hi>all things is vnclean:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> and Christ saith,<note place="margin">Math 7.18,</note>
               <hi>that an euill tree can not bring forth good fruit.</hi> And, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176348:48"/> is not of faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.24.</note> without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>is sinne.</hi> To this doctrine alwaies subscribed the Orthodoxe and ancient Church. The Arausican Councell saith,<note place="margin">Concil. Araus. c. 22. &amp; 20.</note>
               <hi>It is from the gift of God, that we keepe our feete from iniustice:</hi> and, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Nulla bona facit homo—.</note>
               <hi>man doth no good things, which God inables him not to do.</hi> Cyprian saith <hi>Al vve can doe is Gods.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 2. epist. 2. Hierom. gal. 3.</note> Hierome saith, <hi>Without Christ euery vertue is but as a vice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. l 2. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. c. 15.</note> Gregorie, <hi>If faith be not first wrought in our heart, other things can not be good, though they seeme to be so.</hi> Augustine saith expressely,<note place="margin">De nupt. &amp; Concup. l. 1. c. 3 Contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul. l. 4 c. 3.</note> that all the workes of vnbeleeuers are sinnes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause whatsoeuer is not of faith, is sinn. And he saith thus of <hi>Pelagius</hi> the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike:<note place="margin">Epist. 106.</note>
               <hi>Sometimes he poised the power of the will with such equall waights in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ballance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aliquantum ad non pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure.</note>
               <hi>that he might determine how it auailed somwhat to cause vs not to sin: which if it be so, there is no place reserued for the helpe of grace, without which, we say free will hath no force at
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:176348:48"/> all in causing vs not to sinne.</hi> In this speach there are two things worthie obseruation. One,<note place="margin">Nihil ad pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum valere, vel, ad non pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum.</note> that (in Augustines iudgement) freewill of it selfe hath no force at all to cause man not to sinne. Of the same minde is the master of the Sentences, who saith,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. dist. 25. F. non posse no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peccare.</note> that man before he be repaired by grace can not but sinne; though the <hi>Schoole</hi> afterward for the most part dissent from him. The second, that it was the heresie of <hi>Pelagius</hi> to teach, that freewil <hi>SOME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WHAT AVAILETH</hi> to cause vs not to sinne. With this iumps the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Councell of Trent,<note place="margin">Sess. 6. c. 7.</note> when it saith, <hi>Let him be accursed that saith all workes done any vvay before iustification, are sinnes indeed.</hi> For thus it insinuates closely, that will, before the grace of iustification partly helped, and partly of it selfe, can doe that which is good, at the least morally, as they speak. And this is the resolute sentence almost
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176348:49"/> of all Papists. I doubt not therefore to auouch, that the present religion of the Church of Rome reuiues in part the heresie of Pelagius, &amp; in these last daies propounds it again to the world with new varnish and fresh colours. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide this charge, they answer the place of Augustine before alleadged thus: When Pelagius saith, the will is of force not to sinne, his meaning (say they) was,<note place="margin">Bellar. de grat. &amp; lib. arbit. l. 5. c. 11.</note> that, will was of force to cause vs neuer to sinne through the course of our liues. I answer againe, Augustine who knew the meaning of Pelagius, speakes not onely of the life of man but euen of particular actions, as appeares by these words:<note place="margin">Ephe. 95. ad Ianocen.</note>
               <hi>He that praies, lead vs not into temptation, praies that he may not sinne, that is, that he may not do any euill.</hi> Vincentius Lyrinensis tooke this to be the heresie of Pelagius, that man by his owne free-will might doe some good things. For
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:176348:49"/> these are his words:<note place="margin">d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Who before that prophane Pelagius did euer presume that the vertue of free vvill vvas so great, that he did not thinke the grace of God was necessarie for the helping of it in the doing of good things according to euery acte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is obiected to the contrarie, that infidels can do things of the law which are good: and that they haue bin and are indued with many vertues, which are the gifts of God. <hi>Ans.</hi> Infidels may doe things good in their kind, but they cannot do thē well: because they applie thē to wrong endes, as honour, profit, pleasure. And a good thing done to a wrong ende, ceaseth to be good, and is euill in the doer. Againe, the vertues of the Heathen, as they are of God, are good; yet as they are vsed or rather abused of men, they are turned to sinns.</p>
            <p>It is alleadged that wicked Pharao did a good worke, when he saide, <hi>I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:176348:50"/> haue sinned, the Lord is righteous, I and my people are sinners:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>pray for me, &amp;c. Answ.</hi> This confession is good in his kinde, but not good in Pharao: because it proceeded not of loue to God, but of the feare of punishment; and it was made in hypocrisie, because afterward he hardned his heart.</p>
            <p>Further it is alleadged, that Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar a heathen man was rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God for sacking of Tyrus:<note place="margin">Ezech. 29.20.</note> and that God would not haue rewarded him, if his worke had bin a sinne. <hi>Ans.</hi> The reward was temporall: and he was rewarded for his labour only, and not for the goodnes thereof.</p>
            <p>Lastly it may be obiect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, that if we cannot doe good workes by free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of corrupt will, then all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, our eating, drinking, sleeping, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, selling, and whatsoeuer we can doe, is sinne: and no sinne may be done: and therefore nothing must be done.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:176348:50"/>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Actions before named, incident to the life of man, are not sinnes of themselues: for then they might not be done at all: but they are sinnes onely in respect of the manner of doing: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are not done in obedience to God, and referred to him as to their right ende, but by-ends are propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And this is the condition of euery man till he be conuerted, that he can doe nothing but sinne and displease God, euen then when the action is praise-worthie before men.</p>
            <p>The consideration of this doctrine serues to correct the erronious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many, who thinke themselues in good case and highly in the fauour of God, because they are not theeues, murderers, blasphemers, adulterers, &amp;c. But alas, they are deceiued: there is matter ynough of cōdemnation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, though they be no outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous malefactours. For all they doe is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:176348:51"/> sinne before God, till they be renewed by grace. In eating, drinking, sleeping, buying, selling, in all they doe they sinne. Not that eating, drinking, slee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, buying, selling, are sinnes in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, but because they faile in the right manner of doing these actions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in that we can do nothing but sinne till we be regenerate, we are taught to acknowledge our bondage vnder sinne and Satan: yea, we must la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to feele this bondage, &amp; to grone vnder the burden of it. This being don, we must goe further yet, &amp; with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirsting hearts seeke to the Mediatour Christ, who preacheth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerāce to captiues, &amp; withal giues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance from sinne, Satan, hell, death, condemnation, to all such as with tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and bruised hearts flie vnto him.</p>
            <p>The second question is, whether a naturall man by the power of his will may be able to resist and ouercome a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:176348:51"/> tēptation. The<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>v. in. 1. dist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. ar. 2. &amp; Thomas ibid. Bellar. de grat. &amp; libero arb. l. 5. c. 7.</note> Papist answers, that he is able to ouercome lesser and easier temptations of himselfe, yea and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too, if he be helped by God: and that sundry temptations do not exceed the strength of mans nature. But we are to hold and we teach the contrarie, that the will of man since the fall of Adam can not ouercome so much as the least temptation. Because the power wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a temptation should be ouercome, is lost and abolished, that is, the power to nill that which is euill and to will that which is good. And where is no power to resist there can be no resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. When we pray to God, &amp; say, <hi>Lead vs not into temptation,</hi> we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that there is no temptation at all that we can of our selues withstād without the help of God. Peter bidds vs <hi>resist Sathan our aduersarie:</hi> and he shewes the right meanes when he adds these words, <hi>Stedfast in faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:176348:52"/>
            <p>It is obiected that a naturall man can either sinne or not sinne. <hi>I answer:</hi> It is true in regard of actions pertaining to outward gouernment and in regard of open sinnes, murther, theft, adulterie, &amp;c. yet not alwaies true, but onely at some times. For euen the righteous sometime fall into open offences. And though the naturall man occasioned to sinne, abstaine from open offence, yet gets he no victorie. For though he auoid the outward act, yet can not he auoide the wicked inclination of his heart. And the abstinence from out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward sinne is not without sinne. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it proceeds from a person vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, it hath not his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from faith: againe, it is for by-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, for the getting of praise, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of open shame, and not for the honour of God.</p>
            <p>The third question is, whether an vnregenerate man by the power of his
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:176348:52"/> will can obserue the law though not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully, yet in respect of the substance of the act. The doctrine of long time hath bin in schooles and church, that he can: and the doctrine of all papists at this day is, that he can if he be helped by God: and that by his owne strength, he may keep all the morall precepts so as no sinne be cōmitted,<note n="o" place="margin">Bell. de grat. &amp; lib. arbit. l. 5. c. 6. in fine.</note> for some short space of time. But the trueth is, he can not. For if we graunt and suppose an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we must presuppose the ground and beginning thereof. Now the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie or sanitie of will, whereby it was able to will that which is good is the ground of a good act, and it is lost: and therefore there can be no keeping of the law in respect of substance. The substance of the first table is, to loue God with all the heart, soule, strength: and the substance of all negatiue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemēts is, <hi>Thou shalt not lust.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther.</note> And the naturall will can not possibly reach
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:176348:53"/> to the doing of these. It is alleadged, that a naturall man may giue almes &amp; doe iustice to others, and such like. <hi>I answere,</hi> in the substance of any dutie commanded there be two things, the act to be done, and the manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: and that is to do it in faith, with a minde to obey God, and to intend his honour thereby. And this manner of doing a worke is the forme of euerie work, that makes it to be good indeed: and without it, workes commaunded in the law, are but as a bodie without life or soule, or as matter without forme. Will therefore is vnable to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue any one commandement or so much as any one worke of a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in his owne intire substance.</p>
            <p>And it must be remēbred as a maine ground, that the law beside externall dueties requires inward obedience, in knowledge of God &amp; his will, in faith, hope, loue, patience, and the subiection
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:176348:53"/> of our thoughts, wills, and affections to the will of God. In respect of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and spirituall obedience, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost saith, the law is impossible, Rom. 8. ver. 3. and that the wisedome of the flesh can not be subiect to the law of God, v. 7. that this is the yoake which neither we nor our fathers could beare. Act. 15.10.</p>
            <p>Againe it was the heresie of Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,<note place="margin">Aug. de heres. c. 88. Innocent. epist. 93. apud August.</note> that a man by the strength of his owne free-will may keepe al the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God though (as they say) he doth it somewhat hardly. And the Papists are not farre from this when they say, that man by naturall strength may keep the whole law for some litle time.</p>
            <p>The fourth question is, whether na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall corrupted will can any way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and dispose it selfe to his owne conversion &amp; iustification: that is, take away the impediments and make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe apt and capable of his iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:176348:54"/> The<note n="b" place="margin">Scotus in 2. dist. 28. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and▪ ibid.</note> doctrine hath bin for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers hundreds of yeares that will can doe it: and the doctrine of the papists now is, that the will so it be stirred vp by God, can do it. But the certen trueth is, that will can not. The conuersion of a sinner is a creation: and no creature can prepare it selfe to his owne creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That very thing,<note n="c" place="margin">Libertie of grace.</note> whereby a man should prepare himselfe to any good dutie, is lost by Adams fall: and therefore the worke of preparation is Gods and not ours; vnlesse it be possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a man, dead in his sinnes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himself to his own spiritual viuifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: by nature we are seruāts of sinne &amp; our libertie begins in our iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Therefore before we are iustified, we can not so much as will that which is good. Indeed the Israelites <hi>prepared their hearts to seeke the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam 7.</note> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zra <hi>prepared his heart to seeke the law of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But this was the worke of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:176348:54"/> men regenerate, whereby they renued in themselues the purpose of obeying God and of perseuering in dueties of godlinesse.</p>
            <p>The fift and the principall question of all is, whether a naturall man can wil his owne conuersion or regeneration. The learned among the papists teach on this manner.<note n="d" place="margin">Bellar. de gr. &amp; lib. arb. l. 6, c. 15.</note> That will alone by it selfe can not: yet that will can, if it be preuented and stirred vp by some good cogitation cast into the minde and some good desire stirred vp in the heart, and be withall helped and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by God. They vse to open their mindes by these comparisons. The eye in darknesse sees nothing and is as it were without the facultie of seeing: yet if an obiect be set before the eie &amp; light be brought in, then can it see. Againe, a man lies a sleepe in a dungeon,<note place="margin">Coster. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir. c. de lib. arb.</note> and he doth not so much as thinke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth: yet let a man come and call
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:176348:55"/> him, and reach downe a corde vnto him, he will then awake, take hold of the cord, put vnder his arme holes, as Ieremie did, &amp; hāg thervpon. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus helped, he both can and doth come forth of the dungeon. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine we teach is the plaine contrarie, <hi>That will before it be turned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted can not so much as will his owne conuersion.</hi> This followes vpon the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ground: for the power to wil that which is truely good is lost: a power to will our conuersion is a power to will that which is good: therefore the power to will our owne conuersion is lost. Beside preuenting and exciting motions that serue to stirre vp and help the will, there is further required that the will be regenerate, before it can will that which is good: and without this gift of regeneration (which is the true preuenting grace) all externall motions and excitations to that which
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:176348:55"/> is good, are of no effect. For the cause must goe before the effect. Now that the will may affect and will that which is good, the cause is the regeneration thereof: in which is giuen to the will not onely a new action, wherby it wils well, but also a new qualitie, whereby it is able and can will well. And this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of willing well, goes before the act of good will, as the cause before the effect. When a man is dead, chafe him, and rubbe him, put aqua-vitae into him to warme him at the heart: when this is done, take him by the hand, plucke him vp, and bidde him walke: for all this, he will not stirre the least ioynt, neither can he. All chafing and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, all speech &amp; perswasiō, &amp; all helps in the world be in vain, vnles the soule be restored to the body. Euē so no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions offred to the mind, nor good desires to the will, are of any moment, till the image of God standing in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:176348:56"/> which is a conformitie with the will of God, and the very soule of our soules, begin to be restored. Nay, the minde is vncapable of any good thought, and the will of a good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, till God once againe create in them a new qualitie or propertie of holinesse, that the minde in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king may thinke well, and the will in willing may will well, or, will that which is good. For though it be the nature of the will to will or nill, yet the proper and formall beginning of well-willing is the integritie or goodnes of the will. It is obiected, that the will to accept and receiue grace, is in vs before grace be receiued. I <hi>answ.</hi> thus, the first act of wil, whereby the wil in his rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration begins to assent vnto God, &amp; begins to wil to be conuerted, is indeed the worke of the will, (because it is the will that willeth) yet doth it not arise of the naturall strength of the will, but
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176348:56"/> from the grace of God, that reneweth it. For to will to be regenerate, is the effect and testimonie of regeneration begunne. Paul handling the point of the predestination and iustification of a sinner, compares God to a potter, and vs to clay. Now the clay, before it is framed to a vessell of honour, &amp; while it is in framing, it is meerely passiue, &amp; doth nothing at all for the framing of it selfe. When a man is to be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate God takes away the stonie heart,<note place="margin">Ezech. 36.</note> that is, by nature disobedient and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnapt to obey: and he giues a fleshie heart, that is, pliable and flexible to obedience. Now to will to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted is a good thing, and one point of true obedience: and therefore it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes not from the heart of man, till it be mollified and framed by God to that which is good. What hast thou, saith <hi>Paul,</hi> that thou hast not receiued?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> and if thou hast receiued it, why dost
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:176348:57"/> thou boast? Now, if to will to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led were of vs, we haue matter of boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in our selues. Againe he saith, we are not sufficient or able to thinke a good thought as of our selues,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6.</note> but our sufficiencie is of God: much lesse then can we of our selues will or desire to be regenerate. The health and life of the soule is of God, who raiseth vs from death to life: now to will to be healed and to will to liue vnto God, is the beginning of health and life. A certaine Councel saith thus:<note place="margin">Concil. Arau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sic. c. 4.</note>
               <hi>If any man doe auouch, that God doth expect our will, that it may be purged from sinne; and doth not confesse that it is the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the spirit of God in vs, that doth make vs to will to be purged, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists the holy Ghost saying by Salomon, The will is prepared of God.</hi> Augustine saith,<note place="margin">August. in Enchind.</note>
               <hi>It is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth, but in God that sheweth mercie, that all may be giuen to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176348:57"/> God, who both prepares the will of man to be helped, and helps it beeing prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: who preuents him that willeth that he may will, and followes him with helpe that willeth, that he will not in vaine.</hi> They which are bodily sicke, can will to be healed before they beginne to be healed: because they be aliue: but they which are spiritually sicke in sinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their conuersion, are dead in their sinne: and therefore they can neither thinke, or will, or desire their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion. When Christ was about to cure a sicke man, he mooues this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion to him, Wilt thou be healed?<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.6.</note> and so when God is about the worke of regeneratiō in any man, he inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mooues the question in the heart, whether he be regenerate or no: and by this meanes stirres vp a desire to be regenerate. If any man thinke, that by this doctrine, men are regenerate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their wills: I answer, when God
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176348:58"/> beginnes to regenerate vs, he makes vs then willing, beeing otherwise by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnwilling▪ and thus he regenerates vs not against our wills, but with our wills; yet so as the willingnes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate is not of vs but of God. It may be alleadged further, that the Act of the will whereby it wills to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, goes before the acte of God whereby he turnes vs to himselfe: and that otherwise, we are conuerted without our consent, and that God workes vpon vs as vpon a blocke or stone. <hi>Answer.</hi> In respect of time they are both done together: but in respect of order of nature, first the will begins to be turned of God, before it can will to be turned. For euery cause is before his effect, if not in time, yet in prioritie of nature. The wil conuerted, so soone as God hath begunne to renew it, wils to be renewed: and it could not will the conuersion of it selfe, vnlesse it had
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:176348:58"/> formerly tasted the goodnes thereof. And though we first feele the desire to be conuerted before the grace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion, it is nothing: for sometimes we perceiue the effect before the cause: as we see the light of the sunne before the sunne: and we see the light of a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in a house before we see the candle. Therfore to will to be regenerate may be the effect of regeneration begunne, though it first of all appeare. For the better clearing of this our doctrine, I will propound two other questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>The first, whether the will of man by his naturall strength, be any cause of his owne conuersion. The answer of the Papist is, that the wil is a cause with the grace of God: and that both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worke our conuersion; grace as the principall, will as the lesse principal,<note n="b" place="margin">Bellar. de gr. &amp; lib. arb l. 6. c. 15. Sent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and both as causes formally But we teach and hold (as the truth is) that will,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176348:59"/> in the Act of working, effecting, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of our conuersion or regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is no cause at all, but in it selfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered a meere patient or subiect to receiue the grace of conuersion giuen and wrought by God. It is absurd to thinke, that a creature should be a cause of his creation, or a dead man of his quickning. Therefore (as I thinke) the doctrine of them that teach, that there are three efficient causes of mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion, Gods spirit, Gods word, mans will, hath his defect. The spirit is the principall cause, the word in his right vse is the meanes or instrument, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the operation of the spirit is effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. As for the will of man, it stands one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a Patient or obiect of diuine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. It is alleadged, that men which repent, are worthie praise therefore: and this can not well be, vnlesse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance proceede from freedome of will. I <hi>answer:</hi> repentance is praised,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176348:59"/> because it is a thing that pleaseth God, and in that respect praise-worthie: and the repentant person is praised, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is the cause of his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, but because he repents bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto inabled by the mercie of God.</p>
            <p>The second question is, whether the conuersion of a sinner be in the power of mans will a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y way. The answer of the papist is, that our regeneration and conuersion is in part in the power of mans will: so as the will stirred vp can either apply it selfe to the grace of God, or reiect the same. Contrariewise<note n="a" place="margin">Reade Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. instit. lib. 2. c. 3. sect. 10.</note> we teach, that regeneratiō is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the power of mans will, but that it wholly depends on the will of God: &amp; that, when God wil conuert and renue vs, though will for his owne nature be apt to resist, yet in respect of Gods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaungeable will, and in respect of the efficacie of his inward operation, it can
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:176348:60"/> not resist and repell the worke of God. For when God himselfe workes any thing, his worke can not be resisted. For his working of a thing is onely to will it to be: and his will can not be resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted. Now in mans conuersion, he <hi>workes the will and he workes the deed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> and he <hi>causeth men to vvalke in his commandements.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 36.26.</note> Resistance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can not be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Secondly the Scripture euerie where teacheth that our conuersion &amp; saluation wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on Gods wil, &amp; not on the wil of man. Of the distinction of man &amp; man in the matter of saluation Paul allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the testimonie of Moses, <hi>It is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in him that willeth nor in him that runneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.16.</note>
               <hi>but in God that sheweth mercie.</hi> Our Sauiour Christ teacheth that the secrets of the kingdome of God are reuealed to some and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers concealed,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27. Luc. 8.10.</note>
               <hi>because the pleasure of God is so:</hi> and because this gift of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176348:60"/> is giuen to some and not to others. Our conuersion is tearmed a new generation and a new creation: for this cause it can not depend on the will of man at all, because a creature hath not his creation or generation in his owne will so as he may either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or refuse it. And it is a great ouer-shaddowing of Gods grace, to make the hauing or the not hauing of it, to be in the choise of mans will. But the text in hand is obiected. When Christ would haue conuerted Ierusalem, they resisted and would not. <hi>I answer:</hi> there is a double worke of God. One is, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the word and sacraments to offer grace: and this indeed may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted. Of this Christ speakes here, whē he saith, <hi>they would not:</hi> &amp; Stephen whē he saith <hi>they resisted the Holy ghost.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.51.</note> The Lord saith, Gen. 6.2. <hi>My spirit shall not alway striue vvith man:</hi> and Peter applies this striuing of Nohes Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176348:61"/> saying, that <hi>Christ went in spirit and preached,</hi> 1. Pet. 3.19. The second is, when God inwardly by his spirite, turnes, renues, sanctifies the whole man: and this worke can not be resisted by the will of man; no more then La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus could resist the worke of Christ, when he was raised from the dead. If it be said, that this doctrine abolisheth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, because it can not choose and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse the grace of God. <hi>I answere:</hi> the angells of God, which will good and can not will euill, haue neuerthelesse perfect libertie of will. And it is greater perfection of libertie freely and onely to will that which is good, then to be able to will both good and euill. He is at more libertie, that can not be a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, then he which maybe either a free man or a seruant. And a necessitie of yeelding to the will of God is no hurt to our will. For it is a speciall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, to wil that which God wills and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:176348:61"/> nothing else. By all this which hath bin said it appeares, what is the difference betweene vs and the church of Rome in the point of free-will. They say li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of grace to will well is onely weakened, diminished, and held cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue by sinne: we say it is quite lost and abolished by the fall of Adam.</p>
            <p>Againe by the former doctrine, the common question is easilie answered: namely wherein lies the efficacie of Gods grace.<note n="a" place="margin">Thom. cont. Gent. l 3. c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Greg. de Val.</note> Some papists answer that it lies ordinarily in the free consent and cooperation of free-will ioyned with grace. And this seemes directly to be the opinion of the councell of Trent. But<note n="b" place="margin">D. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1. Thom. q. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 22. q. 10.</note> this is much derogatorie to the diuine grace of God to place the efficacie thereof in mans will: and it ministers much matter of boasting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.7.</note> Others place the efficacie of grace in the congruitie of the obiect, that is, in morall perswasions which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:176348:62"/> God knows to be apt and fit to mooue and allure the will according to the condition therof,<note place="margin">Bellar. de grat. &amp; lib. arbit. l. 5. c. 11. Confuted by Molina, as saith P. Bin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld. de lib. arb. p. 591. Stapl. Antido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in Acta.</note> euen as a beast is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the sight of a bottle of hay. But there is no efficacie in these perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons presented to the mind: because the will lies in thraldome and bondage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der sinne and Sathan. And the wil must not onely be helped, but also be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from this bondage, before any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions can mooue it.<note place="margin">Lumb. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. dist. 25.</note> Lumbard in his time much declined from the puritie of the former daies: and yet he is farre founder then the Iesuites of our daies. For he saith thus: <hi>Free-will now is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the law of the flesh from doing good and stirred vp to euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nisi per grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am liberetur &amp; adiuv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>so as it can not will and doe good, vnlesse it be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and helped by grace.</hi> We leauing the papists in their dissentions place the efficacie of grace in the grace it selfe. For Christ saith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.45.</note> Euerie man that hath heard and learned of the father comes
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176348:62"/> vnto me. Againe we place it in this, that God adds the second grace to the first. For hauing giuen the power he staies not there, but proceeds further &amp; giues the will, and with the will the deede. And thus is the grace of God effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall.</p>
            <p>The consideration and vse of this &amp; the former doctrines is of great conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. For if libertie of grace be lost, great is the necessitie of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Christ and great is the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie thereof. Secondly this doctrine cuts off the excuse of all sinne: for though we sinne necessarily because libertie of grace is lost: yet we sinne freely, because libertie in euill remaines. Thirdly it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares hence, that man of himselfe can not haue or retaine any goodnesse, but that which God giueth and preserueth in vs. This thing must moue vs to pray earnestly for the grace we want: and to giue heartie thanks for the graces we
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:176348:63"/> haue. Fourthly we are taught deeplie to hūble ourselues for the losse of our libertie and for the bondage vnder sin: and to pray instantly for deliuerance by Christ. Fiftly, seeing of our selues we can not preuaile against the least temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, we must pray to be guided and assisted continually by God. Lastly, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our conuersion depends on Gods mercie and not on our will, we are taught to denie our owne wills, wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, power; and to ascribe our iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and saluation wholly and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God.</p>
            <p>The third estate of man, is the estate of regeneration: in which the wil hath power to will, partly that which is good and partly that which is euill, as daily experience declareth in the liues of iust men. And the reason is, because the will of man renued, hath in it a three-fold libertie. The first is, the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of nature,</hi> to will or nill which
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:176348:63"/> is in all men. The second is, <hi>libertie of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</hi> whereby the wil when it willeth any euill, willeth it freely. And this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie is diminished according to the measure of grace, which God bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The third is <hi>libertie of grace</hi> to will that which pleaseth God, and it is restored in part in regeneration: so far forth as libertie to sinne is diminished. And because these three alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the will to the death, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sometimes it willeth well, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time euill, sometime both: and in the best actions we doe there is a mixture: because they are not perfectly good for the time of this life, but partly good and partly euill.</p>
            <p>That this power of the will may the better appeare, I will propound foure questions. The first is, whether the will preuented or renued, haue any stroake, action, or operatiō in the first regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a sinner. <hi>I answer:</hi> In the reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:176348:64"/> or conuersion of a sinner I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider two things. First, the beginning or ground thereof, and that is the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or imprinting of new qualities and inclinations in the minde, will, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the heart. And this is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire or meere worke of God in vs and vpon vs: and we in it are <hi>merely pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, not active.</hi> The second is the Eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the former in new and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall actions, as namely in thinking, willing, and desiring that which is good. Now these actions are workes of God in and by mans will: and mans will is not onely a Subiect of them, but also an Instrument. A Subiect, in that God is the first and principall worker of these workes in the will. An Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, because it pleaseth God to vse the will, and to mooue it by his grace for the acting and effecting of the things which he appointeth. And thus the will is not merely passiue, but
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:176348:64"/>
               <hi>passiue</hi> and <hi>actiue</hi> both: first passiue, and then actiue. For beeing acted and mooued by God, who works the will and the deede, it also acteth and moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. And we doe not vtterly denie the Co-operation of mans will with Gods grace. It is necessarie indeed that God first regenerate vs and make vs his children and new creatures. And in this thing, we doe not Co-worke with God, but stand as patients, that God may worke vpon vs and reforme vs euen in the same manner, as when he made vs in the beginning without any helpe of ours. Yet, after our rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratiō, by faith we are brought from life to death, and to will is present with vs, though in weake measure by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the remainders of corruption: and then we begin to be Co-workers with the grace of God, mooued to will and so indeede willing that which is good. In this sense haue the learned
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176348:65"/> said,<note place="margin">Prosper. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Collat. 12. Devoc. Gent. l. 2. c. 29.</note>
               <hi>that which is repaired in vs, is not repaired without vs:</hi> and, that <hi>God in them whome he calls, prepares the will that it may be a receiuer &amp; handmaid of his gifts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same answer in effect I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound an other way. In the worke of our regeneration, three graces be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, the preuenting grace, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king grace, and the co-working grace. The <hi>preuenting grace</hi> is, when God of his mercy sets and imprints in the mind a new light, in the will a new qualitie or inclination, in the heart new affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The <hi>working grace</hi> is, when God giues to the will the acte of well-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, namely<note n="a" place="margin">Velle crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, velle resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscere, velle ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dire.</note> the will to beleeue, the will to repent, the will to obey God in his word. The <hi>Co-working grace</hi> is, when God giues the deede to the will, that is, the exercise and practise of faith and repentance. The first giues the power of doing good,<note place="margin">Aug de grat. &amp; lib. arb. c. 17.</note> the second the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:176348:65"/> will, the third the deede: and all three togither make the worke of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Now the wil of man in respect of operation, doth not concurre with Gods preuenting grace, but is merely patient as a subiect to receiue grace. For it is the proper worke of God to set or imprint a new facultie or inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the will, and that without any action of the saide will. Neuerthelesse the will beeing once renewed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, concurreth by his operation with the working and Co-working grace of God. For the wil beeing moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by grace, willeth and doth indeede that whereto it is mooued. And the will to obey God, or to performe any like dutie, proceedes ioyntly from two causes. From grace: in that it mooueth and causeth the will to will to beleeue. From the will of man: in that beeing preuented and mooued by God, it wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to beleeue, or to do any like dutie.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176348:66"/> And therefore the ancient saying hath his truth, <hi>He that made thee without thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. serm. 15. de verbis Apost.</note>
               <hi>doth not regenerate or saue thee without thee.</hi> Because our conuersion is not without the motion and consent of will, as our creation was. And that we doe not mistake in this point, the order that is betweene mans will and Gods grace, must here againe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. In respect of time they are both together, and concurre in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry first moment of our regeneration: in respect of the order of nature, the will doth not first begin that which is good, and then after borrowe aide from grace: but grace preuents, renues, and mooues the will, and then the will mooued or changed, wils to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and to be healed in the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant of conuersion.</p>
            <p>This operation of the will, to wil to beleeue, to will to repent and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, is the least grace and signe of Gods
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:176348:66"/> fauour: (for nothing can be lesse then to wil to do that which is good:) yet is it of great &amp; excellēt price. For it hath the promise of God annexed to it. The prophet saith to the rebellious Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, <hi>Wash and make you cleane—:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 1.16.</note>
               <hi>cease to doe euill, learne to doe well.</hi> Now they might peraduenture say, Alas, we can not wash our selues: he therefore addes, <hi>If ye will and obey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">vers. 19.</note> that is, if ye doe but will to be clensed, and testifie this will by your endeauour to obey, <hi>ye shall eate the good things of the land.</hi> And Christ saith, that the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father giueth the holy Ghost to thē that desire him.<note place="margin">Luc 11.13.</note> And to them that are in Christ God accepts this Acte of goodwill for the deede it selfe. Marke the comfort that flowes from this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The ful obedience to the law of God is impossible to all men, except Christ, in this life: yea to them which are conuerted and sanctified, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:176348:67"/> desire the fulfilling of the law in themselues: and therefore no man can be iustified by it before God, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine saluation thereby. Neuerthelesse saith in Christ and repentance is so farre forth possible,<note place="margin">Faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance are possible to all that will in earnest.</note> to all that will and haue a desire, that whosoeuer doe but will in earnest to beleeue and to be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, doe indeede beleeue and are conuerted, and please God, and shal not perish eternally, though the beginning of faith and conuersion be weake; so it be in truth and not counterfeit. And yet such is the naughtines of our nature that faith and conuersion, is impossible vnto vs, vnlesse of the singular mercie of God, it be stirred vp in the hearts of the Elect by his holy spirit. In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect Christ saith, Math. 11. <hi>My yoke is easie and my burden light.</hi> And againe, <hi>his commandements are not grieuous.</hi> It may be obiected, that the will &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of renouation and reconciliation
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:176348:67"/> with God, may be where there is a mind and purpose to sinne, and where is no true hatred and detestation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie. <hi>Answ.</hi> The serious and instant will or desire to beleeue in Christ and to repent, includes in it the hatred of sinne, and the purpose of not sinning. For he that truly desires to beleeue doth so: because he detests his vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe: and he that desires to repent: doth so, because he hates his owne euill waies, and purposeth to sinne no more.</p>
            <p>The second question is, whether the will after it is renewed be able to cause and bring forth good workes of it selfe, or no? I answer two things. The first, that will cannot, vnlesse God further giue a double grace. The one is <hi>Assisting grace:</hi> and it stands in three actions, <hi>preseruation, confirmation, protection.</hi> Preseruation is, whereby God continues the being of the will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:176348:68"/> For that which is good, doth not continue good the least moment, vnlesse God make it to continue. Confirmation is, when God fixeth the minde in that which is good and causeth the will constantly to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the good inclination thereof, it being otherwise mutable and apt to decline. <hi>Protection</hi> is whereby God defends his grace in vs against the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of temptation. Of this he saith to Peter,<note place="margin">Luc. 21.</note>
               <hi>Sathan hath desired to sift you, but I haue prayed for thee that thy faith faile not.</hi> And God promiseth that he will not suffer the faithfull to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue that they are able to beare.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> The second grace may be called, <hi>Exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace,</hi> whereby God mooues and stirres vp the will, that it may indeede will and doe the good to be done. And this grace is ordinarily required to the effecting of euerie good worke. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids will was exceedingly renued by
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:176348:68"/> the Holy ghost, yet he prayes still,<note place="margin">Psal. 119.36.</note>
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline mine heart vnto thy testimonies.</hi> The Christian soule, that is alreadie drawne to Christ prayeth still, <hi>Dravv me and we will runne after thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note> Paul saith, they which are the children of God, <hi>are guided, mooued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or stirred by the spirite of God. Againe he saith of the Philippians, after they were renued &amp; wrought their owne saluation with feare &amp; trēbling,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that God did stil <hi>worke in them</hi> beside the power the Act of willing and of doing that which is good. And he works the will, by moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it to will and to doe indeede, that which it can will and doe. And this moouing cause, is the good will of God. It may not seeme straunge, that I say new grace is required to stirre vp the will to the doing of euerie new worke. For grace in the will is like a fire of greene woode which hardlie burnes, and continues not to burne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:176348:69"/> it be continually stirred vp and blowed: euen so the good inclination of the will, because it is ioyned, nay mixed with contrarie corruption that presseth downe, tempteth, inticeth, and draweth away the will from God and all goodnesse, hath neede continually to be excited, stirred and mooued. The man regenerate is able to pray to God, yet can he not pray sometime by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the weight of corruption, vnles the spirite help to beare the infirmities of nature and make request in vs by stirring and moouing vs to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> The doctrine of the auncient church hath beene that,<note place="margin">Aug. ep. 107. Gratia dari ad singulos actus bonos.</note>
               <hi>new grace is to be giuen to the doing of euery good act.</hi> And,<note n="a" place="margin">de praedest. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nctor. c. 11.</note> that we doe not that good which we can doe, vnlesse God make vs doe it, as he made vs able to doe it. This doctrine must the rather be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, because the streame of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish doctrine runnes another way; by
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:176348:69"/> teaching that our wills assisted by grace can doe good,<note place="margin">Ruard. Tapper. Bellar. degr. &amp; lib. arb. l. 6. c. 15.</note> without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of new grace to excite and stirre vp the will. Indeed for the doing of naturall actions the generall Coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God suffiseth: but to the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of actions Supernaturall, the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall help of God is required. A child, that can goe vp and downe in an euen flore being staid by the mothers hand, for all this it can not goe vp a paire of staires vnlesse it be lifted at euerie step. Like is the case of the children of God, in thinges which concerne the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
            <p>The second part of the answere is, that when renued will doth a good worke it doth it not perfectly.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>To will</hi> (saith Paul) is <hi>present vvith me, but I can not performe the good I would,</hi> that is, I can not perfectly doe it as I would. It may be obiected thus. The workes of God are perfect: good workes done
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:176348:70"/> by vs, are workes of God: therefore they are perfect. <hi>I answere</hi> to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior or first part of the reason: it is true of such workes as are workes of God alone, and not of such as are workes ioyntly both of God and man, God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the principall agent, and man the instrument. For then the worke done takes vnto it the qualitie, and condition of man: considering it proceeds from God through the sinnefull minde and will of man. The scriuener, when he writes by himselfe, he writes a perfect hand: but when a learner and he write both together, he taking the learners hand into his owne, then that which is written will carrie the imperfection of the learner. Like is the case in all such workes as are from God in and by vs.</p>
            <p>The third question is, whether the reliques of corruptiō be of that force in sinning, that they can vtterly quench
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:176348:70"/> the spirit of God in the renued will. The answere is, that corruption remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is of it selfe apt to doe it: and the grace of Gods spirit is apt to be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished, because of it selfe it is mutable: neuertheles it wholly &amp; vtterly cannot be lost, for 4 causes. The first is, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of God in the couenant of grace, <hi>I will put my feare into their hearts that they shall not depart from me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note> and this promise particularly belonges to all them that truely beleeue, because it is the promise of the Euangelicall coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. The second is, the Intercession of Christ in the behalfe of all the Elect. Christ saith to Peter,<note place="margin">Luc. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Sathan hath desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to sift you as wheate, but I haue prayed for thee Peter that thy faith faile not. And this he did especially in that solemne praier made Iohn 17. in which he prayed not onely for Peter, but for all the Apostles and for all that did or should beleeue in him. The third
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:176348:71"/> cause is the omnipotent power of God in preseruing all thē that are in Christ, <hi>No man</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>taketh my sheepe forth of my hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28.</note> And marke the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: <hi>my father is greater then all.</hi> The last cause is the Efficacie of Gods spirit. S. Iohn saith, that the seede of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in him that is borne a new: and that this seede keepes him that he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth nor can sin in two respects. First, if he sinne, yet he sinnes not with full consent of will. For he hates and nills in part the euill which he willeth.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note> Secondly, if by humane frailtie he fall, he makes not a trade of sinne, neither doth he keep a course in wickednesse, but the seed of grace remayning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, causeth him to returne to God and to recouer himfelfe by new repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>The last question is, whether the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued will can of it selfe perseuere in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good. I answere, that our perseue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:176348:71"/> dependes and proceedes onely from the will of God. That we may perseuere two things are required: the power to perseuere and the wil of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuerance: and both these being good things are of God. Because euery good giuing and euery good gift is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue and commeth downe from the father of lights.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This former doctrine is of great vse. In that the new birth &amp; regeneration of a sinner is not without the motiō of his owne will, we are taught, that we must if we desire our owne saluation, vse the good meanes, and striue against our owne corruptions, and endeauour earnestly by asking, seeking, knocking. It wil be said, that faith, repentance and the rest, are all giftes of God. I answer, there is no vertue or gift of God in vs, without our wills: and in euerie good act, Gods grace &amp; mans will concurre: Gods grace as the principall cause:
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:176348:72"/> mans wil renewed as the instrument of God. And therefore in all good things industrie and labour, and Inuocation on our parts is required.</p>
            <p>Secondly this doctrine ministers true cōfort to all true seruants of God. For, if when they vse the good meanes of saluation, the word, praier, sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the will lie not dead but begin to oppose it selfe against vnbeleefe, and other corruptions, and withall doe but so much as will to beleeue, will to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, will to be turned to God, they haue begunne to turne vnto God, and God hath begun to regenerate them; so be it, this will in them to doe the good they ought to doe, be in good earnest vnfained, and they withall be carefull to cherish this little graine, till it come to a bigger quantitie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, seeing to euery new act that pleaseth God, new grace is required, we are taught not to presume of our
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:176348:72"/> owne wisdome, will, and strength; nor to glorie in any thing we doe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to acknowledge our owne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie, and in euery good thing we doe, to giue all the glorie to God: and to be watchfull in praier continually, because we stand by grace so long as we stand: and hauing done one worke, we doe not the second but by a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued supplie of new grace.</p>
            <p>Lastly seeing Gods preuenting and working grace turnes our wills and makes them of vnwilling most willing wills, all our obedience must be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, and come from such freenesse of will, as if there were no bond in the law of God to force and compell vs thereto.<note place="margin">Psal. 110 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The people of God that are turned and guided by the free spirit of God, must be a voluntarie people, and with all alacritie and cheerefulnes doe the duties that pertaine to them, of a readie minde, euen as if there were
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:176348:73"/> neither heauen nor hell, iudge nor iudgement after this life. The spirit of life that is in Christ must be a law vnto them.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The last estate is the Estate of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification after this life. In this estate the Libertie of will is a certen freedom onely to will that which is good and pleasing vnto God. For it is the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall voice (as it were) and crie of the glorified will; <hi>I doe no euill, and I will not doe it: I doe that which is good, and I will doe it.</hi> And this indeed is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Libertie in which mans wil is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Free-will of God and good angels, who will onely that which is good, and can not will that which is euill.</p>
            <p>By this which hath bin saide, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that the wordes of the text in hand <hi>[and ye would not]</hi> are spoken of the will of man according to the estate of corruption. For the voice of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:176348:73"/> will is, <hi>I doe that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill but I would not doe it: I doe that which is good, but I can not doe it as I would.</hi> And the voice of the corrupted will is, <hi>I doe that which is euill, and I will doe it: I doe not that which is good, and I will not doe it.</hi> And this last voice is plainely expressed in these wordes, <hi>And ye would not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third point comes now to be considered, namely the <hi>Harmonie</hi> or <hi>consent of both wills.</hi> For the wordes are, <hi>I would, ye would not.</hi> Here it may iustly be demanded, whether there be an Harmonie or consent betweene Gods will and mans will, and how it stands with this text. I answer, there is an excellent harmonie: and generally it stands in this, that Gods will hath a soueraigne Lordship ouer the will of man, and mans will stands subiect to it absolutely, and simply depends vpon it. And by this meanes, where man hath a
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:176348:74"/> will, God hath an antecedent will; and where mans will hath any stroke or action, there Gods will formerly had his stroke and action.</p>
            <p>Furthermore mans will depends on Gods will, in respect of three things, namely <hi>Sustentation, Determination, Ordination,</hi> or gouernmēt. It depends on the will of God in respect of susten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: because mans wil for his nature, strength, and all his motions depends on the will of God: and could not haue beeing for the space of one moment, vnlesse it were vpholden by God. It may be <hi>obiected,</hi> that if God sustaine the will which is sinnefull he sustaines not onely the will but also the sinne thereof. <hi>Answ.</hi> God sustaines nature, and not the sinne of nature: &amp; threfore he only sustaines will as will, and not as it is corrupt or sinnefull will. The like we see in nature: when a man halts in walking, the motion of the bodie is
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:176348:74"/> from the soule, and is preserued by it: but the halting which goes with the motion and disorders it, is not from the soule, neither hath it his preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thence, but frō a defect in the legge or foote. By this we are taught to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the endlesse long-suffering of God, who sustaines the members of our bodies, our soules, the faculties and actions thereof, euen in the workes in which men offend &amp; dishonour him. Secondly we are taught to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the vile abhomination of euery sinne: for we sinne in the very hands of God sustaining and preseruing vs: and in the very actions, which we could not doe vnlesse we were sustained by him, we offend him and prouoke him to anger against vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly mans will depends on Gods will in respect of determination: because we netiher can nor doe will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing without the will of God. A
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:176348:75"/> sparrow, saith Christ, lights not on the ground <hi>without the heauenly father,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Math. 20.29.</note> without his decree or will. The malitious and wicked wil of the Iewes could not so much as will, much lesse doe any thing against Christ, but that <hi>which the hand and counsell of God had determined to be done.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.28.</note> Moreouer God determines the will two waies. In good things he inwardly mooues and inclines the will to the willing and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the good it willeth. For in that Gods will is the first cause of all good things, mans will depends on it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of vertue, in respect of Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in respect of order of working. In respect of vertue:<note place="margin">Thom. 1. par. q. 105. atr. 5.</note> because the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of second causes proceed from the first. In respect of Application: because God vseth the will of man as an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his owne will, and he applieth it to the doing of things which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth, euen as the carpenter vseth,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:176348:75"/> mooueth, and applieth his tooles. In respect of order of working: because alwaies the first cause begins the work, and the second mooues not without the first. Vpon this ground it follows, that the good things which man wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, he so willeth, because God first willed them. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that good workes <hi>are prepared of God</hi> for vs to walke in:<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> and this preparation is made, because God decrees and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines with himselfe the doing of all works to be done.</p>
            <p>In euill things the Determination of God is<note n="b" place="margin">Vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> impedite.</note> to will not to hinder them as he may. Vpon this will in God fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes sinne in the will of man, as a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequent, not as an effect. As a consequēt: because when God suspends or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes sustentation and gouernment from the will, it cannot of it selfe but will amisse: as the staffe in my hand presently falls when I do but pull backe
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:176348:76"/> my hand. To auoide euill is good: and therefore we cannot auoide the least euill, vnlesse God make vs able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide it.<note place="margin">Voluntas per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iua effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax non quoad productionē, sed quoad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem.</note> And <hi>[c]</hi> euill is not the effect of Gods wil: because God puts nothing into mans will to cause it to wil amisse: but he onely ceases to conferre vnto it helpe and direction, which he is not bound to conferre.</p>
            <p>Here long and tedious disputes are made by many touching the Concord of Gods decree and the libertie of mās will. And it is alleadged that mans will looseth his libertie and ceaseth indeede to be will, if it stand subiect to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie and vnchaungeable decree of God. I answer, first that when the will of man determines it selfe to one thing, it doth not loose his libertie: much more then may the libertie of will stād with the determination of God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly Gods decree doth not abolish libertie but onely moderate and order
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:176348:76"/> it: by<note n="a" place="margin">Suauiter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinando.</note> inclining the will in milde and easie manner with fitt and conuenient obiectes and that according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the will. That Christ should die when he died, it was necessarie in respect of Gods decree: yet if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect the constitution of his nature he might still haue prolonged his daies: &amp; if we consider the will of Christ, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed most freelie and willingly. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise his death had bin no satisfaction for sin. God himselfe doth some things of an absolute necessitie, and yet with perfect freedome of will: now then if absolute necessitie doe not abolish free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of will, much lesse shall conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall necessitie depending on Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, doe it. Lastly, the decree of God establisheth the libertie of will. For his determination is, that the Agencie of second causes shall be according to their condition: so as naturall causes shall worke naturally: free causes, freely:
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:176348:77"/> necessarie causes, necessarily: contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent causes, in contingent and variabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> sorte. And therefore the necessarie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God is, that man shall will this or that, not necessarily in respect of himselfe, but freely.</p>
            <p>Thirdly mans will depends on Gods will in respect of gouernment. This gouernment is of two sortes. First he gouernes the wills of the righteous, by working his owne good worke in them and by them. In them, because he mooues and inclines them by his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. By them: because they are holie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of his will.</p>
            <p>Secondly he gouernes the wills of the wicked and vngodlie by sixe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The first is <hi>permission,</hi> when God withdrawes his grace from the will, not inlightning the minde nor incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the will, but leauing it to it selfe; as when a man giues the rene to a wilde horse. The second is, a <hi>deliuerie of the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:176348:77"/> will to Sathan,</hi> and that is when God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iues the diuell libertie to tempt,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. last. 1. Cor. 5.</note> assault and vexe the will of man being left to it selfe. And this thing is incident to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate sinners: and we pray against it in these words, <hi>Lead vs not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> The third action is, a <hi>ceasing to restraine</hi> corruption of will, either in whole or in part: as whē he restraines al sinnes, saue one, or, hauing restrained for a time, for the punishment of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer sinne, he omits restraint, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting man to the lusts of his owne heart. The fourth action is, the <hi>bending, moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, or inclining</hi> of the wicked will. And this God doth not by inward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration (for then he should be the cause of sinne) but by presenting to the minde and will obiects good, or at the least indifferent in themselues: vpon which obiectes the will takes occasion to be more willfull, obstinate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, not mooued thereto by God,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:176348:78"/> but freely moouing it selfe. The heate of the stomacke in the winter season, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> increased, not by the heate of thinges taken inwardly but by the cold of the aire euerie way compassing the body. An vnbroken horse being spurred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he goes out of order; he flinges out and castes his rider. And thus the sinnefull will of man vrged by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, threatnings, iudgements: allured by promises and blessings, growes more sinnefull and wicked. Paul saith that <hi>sinne tooke occasion vpon the good commandement of God</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue and to be sinfull out of measure.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.8.15.</note> Dauid saith, that God <hi>moued the hearts</hi> of the Egyptians <hi>to hate his people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 105.25.</note> But how? He blessed the Israelites excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, more then the Egyptians. And vpon this worke of God, they tooke occasion to enuie and to hate the Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites.</p>
            <p>The fift action is <hi>ordination,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:176348:78"/> God vseth well, the wickednesse of the wil of man, and directeth it against the nature thereof to good endes, euen as the learned physicion sometime of poyson makes a remedie. In this sense Assur is called the <hi>rod of his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and the Medes &amp; Persians,<note place="margin">Isay. 10.5. &amp; 13.3.</note>
               <hi>his san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified ones.</hi> The Iewes in the crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Christ <hi>vvilled and minded</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his death and destruction: yet God willed and by them wrought the redemption of mankinde. He workes his owne good worke by mans will, as by an actiue instrument, and withall he leaues the will to it selfe, to worke his owne euill worke. The last action of God is, when a man is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in his owne wickednesse, <hi>he turnes him vnto himselfe,</hi> of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding mercie: and sometimes againe he <hi>opens a way,</hi> that that person, who of himselfe runnes into wickednesse, may rush headlong to his owne destruction
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:176348:79"/> for the further exequution of diuine iustice: as when an house is falling th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> owner thereof will not vnderpropp it, neither will he push it downe: but he takes away al impediments and digges away the earth round about it, not touching the foundation, that when it falls, it may fall downe right.</p>
            <p>Thus we see brieflie the harmonie of mans will and Gods will: now let vs come to the vse, which is manyfold. First of all, by the former doctrine, we are brought to a right vnderstanding of many places of scripture. The Lord saith of Pharao,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.21.</note>
               <hi>I will harden his heart.</hi> And this he is said to doe, not because he setts and imprintes hardnesse in his heart, but because by sundrie actions he orders and gouernes his wicked will, and they are foure. First he permits Pharao to his owne will: secondly he leaues him to the malice of the diuell and the lustes of his owne heart: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:176348:79"/> he vrges him with a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to let the people goe. And Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao the more he is vrged, the stiffer and stubberner he is, &amp; the more he rebells against God, wheras he ought indeed to haue bin the more obedient. Lastly God vseth the hardnesse of Pharaos heart to the manifestation of his owne iustice and iudgement, and therefore he opens him a way that he may runne headlong to his owne destruction. In this manner, and no otherwise are the places to be vnderstoode, when the Scripture saith,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 22.23.</note> that <hi>God put a lying spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into the mouthes of the prophets of Ahab:</hi> that, <hi>if a prophet be deceiued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 14.9.</note>
               <hi>the Lord deceiued him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.28.</note> that <hi>he giues vp men to reprobate mindes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that <hi>he senas strong illusions to beleeue lies.</hi> In the booke of Samuel it is saide,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>the Lord commanded Shemi to curse Dauid:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause about this cursing there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold actiō in God. One, that he restrains
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:176348:80"/> the wicked heart of Shemi in respect of all other sinnes, and not in respect of this sinne of railing, to which God leaues him. The second, he vseth him as an instrument to correct and to hū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dauid. And thus likewise must the places be vnderstood, when it is saide, that <hi>God deliuered the wiues of Dauid to Absolom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.11. and 24.1.</note>
               <hi>and that he stirred vp Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to number the people.</hi> Lastly Ioseph saith, that <hi>the Lord sent him into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> and that for two causes. One, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause when his brethren were about to make him away, God by his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence caused marchants to passe by in their sight, whereupon they tooke oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to sell him into Egypt. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, because God disposed this fact of theirs to the good of Iacob and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie in time to come. And thus are all like places of Scripture to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode.</p>
            <p>Againe, some schoole-Diuines fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:176348:80"/> Damascen, make &amp; ascribe to God an applied or depending will, on this manner. God for his part would haue all men without exception to be saued: why then are they not saued? They thēselues will not. And because they will not, God therefore chooseth some and refuseth others. But accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the former doctrine, I take this kinde of applied will, to be an inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans braine. For the contrarie is the truth, namely that mās will wholly depēds on the will of God. That vessels be some of honor, some of dishonor, it is not in the power of the clay, but in the will of the potter. The first cause orders the second, and not the second the first. To make Gods wil depend on mans will, is to put God out of his throne of maiestie, and to set the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in his roome. Others set forth the depending wil of God on this manner. God (say they) decrees nothing in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:176348:81"/> of things that are casuall &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent,<note place="margin">Bellar. l. 4. c. 15. de grat. &amp; lib. arbit. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard. Tapper.</note> but he foresees within himselfe what the will of the creature will doe or not doe, when things are thus or thus ordered: and vpon this foresight he consequently determines what shall be done. But this opinion, as it giues vnto God a common or generall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, so it takes away the certen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of God touching all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular euents. And it is absurd to think that God should foresee the future acts of mans freewill, when as yet he hath determined nothing: for things that shall be, are therefore to come to passe, because God by decree hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their beeing. And therefore the foreknowledge of things that shall be followes the decree of God. And if Gods decree presuppose mans willing of this or that, and thereupon deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, how shal that speach of the Lord stand,<note place="margin">Ezech. 36.26.</note>
               <hi>I will cause them to walke in my
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:176348:81"/> statutes.</hi> For hereby is signified, that God doth not attend on the will of man, but brings mans will in subiection to himselfe.<note place="margin">Shumel in 1. Thomae. q. 19. art. 6.</note> And therefore this atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding will ascribed to God, is improo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued euen of the Papists themselues.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that mans wil stands sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect absolutely to the pleasure of God, our dutie is, to yeelde voluntarie subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to him in all things when his wil is made manifest vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Lastly, this doctrine of the consent and concurrence of mans will &amp; Gods will, must be the stay and ground of our patience and comfort. For there is no calamitie or miserie that betides vs by and from the will of man, without the will of God. The creature can will nothing against vs vnlesse it be first the will of God: and it can doe neither more nor lesse then God will. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil could not touch Iob without leaue, and he could not enter into the heard
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:176348:82"/> of swine without leaue. Vpon this ground Dauid speakes to this effect, Let Shemi curse, for <hi>he curseth because the Lord bids him doe so.</hi> Ioseph com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts himselfe and his brethren in this, that not they so much as the Lord sent him into Egypt.</p>
            <p>As there is an Harmonie betweene Gods wil &amp; mans wil: so there is a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent between mās will &amp; Gods word, or his signifying will, as appeares by the text in hand.<note n="a" place="margin">Hales 3. Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae q. 69 Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas in 1. 2 q. 109. &amp; contra Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iles. l. 3 c. 159. Roffensis in refutant. 36. Bell. de grat. &amp; lib. arb. l. 2. c. 5.</note> Schoolemen vpon this dissent make a distinction of Gods grace into sufficient and effectuall. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient they call that whereby a man may be saued, if he will not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to himselfe. Effectuall, whereby a man is indeede saued. The first (they say) is giuen to all men at one time or other, the second is not. And this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction of grace they gather on this manner. When Christ would haue gathered the Iewes, they would not:
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:176348:82"/> therefore they had not effectuall grace: and because they would not, they are blamed and rebuked by Christ: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (saith the Papist) God gaue them sufficient grace to be conuerted, if they would: els could he not haue blamed them. <hi>I answer,</hi> this prooues that once God gaue them sufficient grace to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey any commandement of his, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the creation: but hence cannot be gathered, that when God called the Iewes by his word, that then, then I say, he gaue them sufficient grace. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly</hi> it is obiected, that God did all that might be don to his Vine to make it bring forth good fruit;<note place="margin">Isa. 5.4.</note> and yet for all this, it brought forth nothing but wild grapes: therefore it is saide, there must needs be a grace sufficient to saluation, which is not effectuall. I <hi>answer:</hi> God did that to his vineyard that was suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make a good vine bring forth fruit, (and that is the meaning of the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:176348:83"/> place in Isai) though not sufficient to change the nature of an euill vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and to make it a good vine. It is vrged, that the Lord saith, he waited for grapes: which he would not haue done, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse there had been hope by reason of sufficient grace giuen. I <hi>answer</hi> again, that the Lord waited for fruit, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God then gaue them sufficient grace when he waited, but because the Church of the Iewes, was in shew and pretence a good vine: and thereby gaue hope of good fruit. <hi>Thirdly</hi> it is obiected that Adam receiued sufficient grace: and that he had not effectuall grace because he fell. I <hi>answer,</hi> Adam had sufficient to the perfection of a creature, but not sufficient to vnchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable perseuerance, specially if he should be assaulted by temptation. Likewise he had grace effectuall in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of righteousnesse and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but not in respect of perseuerance
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:176348:83"/> in both. Grace in him, so farre forth as it was sufficient to happinesse, it was also effectuall. <hi>Lastly,</hi> it is obiected, that God forsakes no man, till he first for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake God: and therefore that God for his part giues grace sufficient to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Answ.</hi> There is a double kind of forsaking in God, one is for triall, the other for punishment. The forsaking which is for trialls sake, goes before mans sinne, in which he forsakes God. In this regard, Adam was for order of nature first forsaken of God, before he forsooke God. The forsaking which is for punishment alwaies followes after sinne, and of this must the rule be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, that they which are forsaken of God, did first forsake God. Now the trueth which we are to hold in this point is thus much. There is a grace which is sufficient to the conuiction of a sinner, which is not effectuall to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and againe there is a grace which
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:176348:84"/> is sufficient to the leading of a ciuill life, which is not effectuall to saluation: yet the grace which is indeed sufficient to saluation, is also effectuall; namely the gift of regeneration, in which God giues not onely the power to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, but also the will and the deed.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the Harmonie: nowe comes the fourth point to be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, namely in what manner Christ willed the conuersion of Hierusalem. He willed it first <hi>in Loue,</hi> secondly <hi>in Patience.</hi> His loue is set forth by two things. The first, albeit he was God full of maiestie, and we vile wretches his enemies by nature, yet was he content to take vpon him a vile and base con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to be vnto the Iewes as an Hen. The second was, that he takes vnto him the fashions, the disposition and tender affection of the Henne to her young ones.</p>
            <p>That all this may the better be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:176348:84"/> three questions are to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. The first is, whether there be such an affection of loue in God, as is in man and beast? I answere, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the creature are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly incident vnto God, because they make many changes, and God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out change. And therefore all affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and the loue that is in man and beast is ascribed to God by figure: and that for two causes. First because there is in God an vnchangeable nature that is well pleased with euery good thing, and a will that seriously willeth the preseruation of euery good thing: and of this nature and will of God, the best loue in the creature is but a light shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. Secondly the affection of loue is ascribed to God; because he doth the same things that loue makes the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doe: because he bestoweth bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings and benefits vpon his creature, as the louer doth on the person loued. In
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:176348:85"/> this sort are all other affections ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to God, and no otherwise.</p>
            <p>The second question is, whether there be in God an hatred of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: for God is cōpared to the Henne which loueth all her young ones. <hi>Ans.</hi> If hatred be taken for a passion inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to man, it is not incident to God: if it be taken for a worke of Gods prouidence and iustice, it is in God: and that in three respects. First of al, in scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Hatred sometime signifies a deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of loue and mercie: as when it is said that he which will follow Christ, <hi>must hate father and mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14.26.</note> that is, neglect them or not loue them in respect of Christ. In this sense hatred agrees vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. For he is said to loue Iacob and to hate Esau:<note place="margin">Rom. 9.13.</note> that is, not to loue Esau with that loue wherewith he loued Iacob. Againe there is in God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nature that abhorreth and detesteth iniquitie, thus saith the psalmist, that <hi>God loueth
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:176348:85"/> righteousnesse and hateth iniquitie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 44.8.</note> And thus God hates man not simply, because he is the handiworke of God, but because he is a sinner, and by reason of the worke of the deuill in man, namely sinne, which is simply hated of God. Thirdly God plagueth and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth offenders, and in this regard he is said to hate them. Thus saith Dauid, <hi>that God hates the workers of iniquitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 5.6.</note>
               <hi>and destroies them that speake lies.</hi> By this which hath beene said, it appeares that there be two degrees of hatred in God: one is <hi>Negatiue,</hi> when God as an absolute Lord, bestowes his speciall loue on some, and denies it vnto others because his pleasure is so. The second is <hi>Positiue,</hi> when he hates and detests his creature: and this second alwaies fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes sinne and is euer for sinne: but the other goes before sin. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is said in this text, that God is as the Henne that loueth all her chickins, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:176348:86"/> gathereth them all together: it must be vnderstood that our Sauiour Christ here sets downe his dealing not with all his creatures and with all mankind; but onely his dealing toward his owne Church, in which he calleth all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by the sound of his word, and receiues all outwardly into the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. By this which hath beene said, we are taught after the example of God to hate &amp; detest iniquitie: and yet alwaies to make difference betweene the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and the sinne.</p>
            <p>The third question is, in what thing is Christ as an henne to his Church? <hi>Answ.</hi> In temporall blessings and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerances: in afflictions and manifold corrections: but specially and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his word published in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of the prophets. For it is the wing which he spred ouer his people: and it is the voice whereby he called and (as it were) clocked them vnto him.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:176348:86"/>
            <p>Thus we see the meaning of the si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, that Christ would haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Hierusalem as the Henne ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her chickins: nowe followes the vse. By this we see the tender loue of God to this Church and land. For it hath pleased him to propound vnto vs the gospell of saluation, and that nowe more then 40. yeres. And in so doing he hath offered long to imbrace vs in the armes of his mercy: and in sprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his wing ouer vs to become our God and our Sauiour: for this tender loue, our hearts must be filled with loue to Christ, and our mouthes with praise.</p>
            <p>Againe, we learne hence, that the gospell brings all other blessings of God with it. For God in it communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates his owne selfe vnto vs as the Hen to her young ones. The kingdome of God brings all things else with it that may serue for the good of man: and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:176348:87"/> where the gospell is imbraced there is Gods kingdome. The peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of this Church and land, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we haue bin preserued from beeing a pray to our enemies, comes by meanes of the gospell of life. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore foolish and false is the conceit of sundrie popish persons that say there was neuer such plentie in the world, as when the olde learning (as they say) or old religion was. Secondly by this we are aduertised, if we would haue all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie blessings for this life, first of all to imbrace the gospell of Christ.</p>
            <p>Thirdly if Christ take vnto him the disposition of the Henne: we likewise must take vnto vs the disposition of the chicken in respect of Christ, and that in three things. First we must suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our selues to be gathered to Christ: that is, to be turned vnto him from all our sinnes, to beleeue in him, to be of the same minde and disposition with
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:176348:87"/> him, to suffer him to quicken vs with his heauenly and spirituall life, as the henne cherisheth her chickins by sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on them. Secondly we must at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon the word and wil of Christ, as the chickin vpon the call of the hen: and suffer him to rule vs both in heart and life, for all things. The third thing is, that we must depend on the sweete and mercifull promises of Christ, and shroud our selues vnder his wing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst hell, Sathan, death, damnation. And verely, all such among vs, who are not carefull to performe these three things to Christ, are no better then monstrous rebels, considering he hath in his mercifull and tender loue, sought to win vs to himselfe for the space of this 40. yeares.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the loue of Christ: nowe I come to his patience in these words: <hi>Howe often would I?</hi> The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whereof is this: you haue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:176348:88"/> from time to time prouoked me by your sinnes: yet did I not withdraw my loue from you, but sent my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets from time to time vnto you, to call you and gather you vnto me And this patience of God is here expressed, to aggrauate the rebellion of Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. I will therefore speake a little of it. And first, it may be demanded, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the vertue of patience that is in men, be also in God. I answer, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is not. For where this kind of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is, there is passion and sufferance: now God is not subiect to any passion or sufferance, because his nature is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable. Againe that which is in God properly, is in him eternally: this patience is not in him eternally, but for the time of the continuance of this world. Neuertheles, Scripture ascribes this patience to God for two causes. The first is, because there is in God an infinite goodnesse of will and nature,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:176348:88"/> wherby he neuer simply wills the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or destruction of any creature. Thus saith Ezechiel, <hi>God wills not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that is, takes no delight in the death of a sinner. And whereas it is said, <hi>that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is Gods and he will repay,</hi> it must be thus taken, that God in reuēge doth not absolutely intend to destroy, but onely to exequute iustice in the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of sinne. It may be obiected, that God is saide <hi>to make vessells of vvrath prepared to destruction.</hi> I answer,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.10.</note> this place must circumspectly and warily be vnderstood: and I take the meaning of it to be this, that God makes vessels of wrath or vessells for wrath by his will and decree, whereby he decrees to passe by some and to forsake them in respect of his loue and mercie. And this acte of God in passing by and in forsaking of men, is as it were, to set them a part to becom vessels of wrath. And though God in secret and iust
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:176348:89"/> iudgement doe this, yet he neuer fills any of these vessels with his wrath, till they haue bin tainted with iniquitie: and though they be prepared to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, yet they are neuer indeede destroied but for their sinnes. Thus then, by reason of this excellent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehensible goodnesse of God, whereof the vertue of patience is but a shadow, God is said to be patient.</p>
            <p>The second cause, why God is saide to be patient is, because he doth the same things that patient men doe. First he inuites men to repentance: secondly he promiseth pardon: thirdly he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres punishment: fourthly at the first he onely inflicts lesser punishments, when they doe no good he inflicts greater: and lastly when there is no hope of amendment, he inflicts euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting death and destruction.</p>
            <p>The ende of Gods patience is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: one that the Elect of God may be
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:176348:89"/> gathered and called: the other, that all excuse might be taken from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.<note place="margin">Rom. 9.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The patience of God is either vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall, or particular. Vniuersall, which pertaines to all men. The decree of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine iustice was set downe to Adam, &amp; in him to all mankind, When thou shalt eate of the forbidden fruit <hi>in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou shalt DIE,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> presently die the first and second death.<note place="margin">Numb. 16.3.</note> Dathan and Abiram presently vpon their rebelliō, went downe into the earth quick. The captaines with their fifties were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently vpon their comming to Elias,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 1.10.</note> destroied with fire from heauen. And so oft as any man sinnes, he deserues present destruction: and so many sinnes as we haue committed, so many dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations haue we deserued. Here it may be demanded, why God doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute his decree accordingly. I answer, God in iustice remembers mercie, yea
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:176348:90"/> his iustice giues place to mercie. For there is an other decree of mercie, which he will haue as well to be accō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished as the decree of iustice, and that is, <hi>The seede of the woman shall bruise the serpents head.</hi> Againe, <hi>Aske of me and I vvill giue thee the heathen for thine inheritance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 2.8.</note>
               <hi>and the endes of the earth for thy possession.</hi> That mercie then may be shewed vpon mankind, iustice is exequuted in great patience by certen decrees. And this patience pertaines to all men without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that come of Adam by generation.</p>
            <p>Speciall patience is that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns particular men or cuntries. Thus God spared the olde world 120 yeares before he sent the flood: he spared the Amorites till their iniquities were full: he spared the Egyptians 400 yeares.<note place="margin">Ezech. 4 5.</note> He deferred the punishment of the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie of Israel 390 yeares, and then he punished it with 70 yeares captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:176348:90"/> He winked at the ignorance of the Gentiles 4000 yeares. Antichrist shall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>terly be destroied till the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Christ. Whē men blaspheme God and Christ, swearing wounds, blood, heart, sides, nailes, life; if they had their desert, they should descend to hell quicke and that presently: but God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares them, and sundrie such persons are vouchsafed the grace of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The very least offender vpon earth is partaker of the great patience of God. For he sustaines the members of our bodies, the powers and motions of the soule in such actions in which we offend him. And no creature can sufficiently consider the greatnesse of this long-suffering.</p>
            <p>The vse to be made of the patience of God follows. First, it serues to teach all men to turne to God by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Rom. 2.4. <hi>Despisest thou the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long-suffering of God, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:176348:91"/> that the goodnes of God leads thee to repentance.</hi> 2. Pet. 3.9. <hi>God is patient towards vs, and would haue no man to perish, but would all men to come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> To come more neere to our selues and this English nation. Now is the day of our visitation, and hath bin for the space of this fourtie yeares and more, in which God in great patience hath continually called vpon vs, knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at the dore of our hearts, and stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out the armes of his mercie vnto vs. Wherefore the common dutie of all English people is, to turne vnto God with all their hearts according to all the law of God, as it is said of Iosias. And that this dutie may indeed be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised, I will vse certaine reasons, that may serue to stirre vp our dead minds. First, the time of the continuance of the patience of God is hiddē &amp; vnknowne vnto vs. And hereupon, when men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busing the patience of God shall say,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:176348:91"/> peace, peace, then, then shall come sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den destruction,<note place="margin">1. Thess. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 5.15.</note> as trauaile vpon a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. And therefore the time is to be redeemed, and as S. Peter saith,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.11.</note> we must watch and make hast for the cōming of the Lord. Secondly, the greater the patience of God is and hath beene, the greater shall his anger be. A blow, the longer it is in comming, the greater it is. Yea the very wrath of God in it selfe is most horrible. The wrath of a lyon, of a Prince, yea the wrath of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the wrath of God,<note place="margin">Mich. 1.</note> is but a droppe of water to the whole sea. At his indignation the very mountaines melt; the heauens &amp; the elements shall melt at his cōming: much more should our rockie &amp; stony hearts melt. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God hath his treasurie &amp; storehou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses for iudgement: and they which goe on in their sinnes from day to day fill this treasurie of God, with wrath and iudgements against the day of wrath.<note place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:176348:92"/> And whē men turne heartily frō their euill waies, this treasurie is emptied, as appears by the exāple of the Niniuites. Wherefore let vs all frō the highest to the lowest bethinke our selues what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil we haue done, and how we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused the mercifull patience of God, &amp; make speed to turne to God and Christ our mercifull Sauiour. Some will say, we abuse not Gods patience; we haue repented long agoe. I answer, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that truly turne vnto God in their hearts is but small in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, euen as the gleaning is to the whole haruest. It will be said againe, we are not as the Iewes that denied Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ to be the Messias. I answer: we confesse Christ in word, but there is a great multitude among vs, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him in their deedes and naughtie liues. For to omit the sinnes of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table, there be fiue notorious sins that are common among vs. Wilfull
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:176348:92"/> ignorance; in that men haue little or no care to knowe God and to knowe the way of life. The secōd is, the prophane contempt of the gospell. For nowe the obedience to this blessed doctrine of life, yea the very shewe of it is in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reputation Precisenes. And now a daies vnder this name, the profession of the gospell comes otherwhiles vpon the stage to helpe to make vp the plaie, &amp; to minister matter of mirth. Vpon this we may iustly feare the gospell is going frō vs. The third sin is worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which raignes and beares sway in all places as though there were no other world, and as though heauen were vpon earth. The fourth sinne of our daies is Lewk-warmnesse. For cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly men are not lost in themselues that they might be found of Christ, they feele not their owne pouertie, they knowe not in what neede they stand of the blood of Christ: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:176348:93"/> they make profession of the faith formally, not seriously, onely because they are forced so to doe by the good lawes of a good prince. The last sinne is Hypocrisie, for all among vs come to the Lords table, and thereby enter into the highest degree of Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that can be vpon earth. For thereby they make profession that they are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to Christ, and haue fellowshippe with him and grow vp therein. And yet the most beeing departed from this holy sacrament, take libertie to liue as they list, despising all others that will not say and doe as they doe. These and many others, are the cōmon fruits of our English vineyard. It stands vs all in hand to pray vnto God,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.16.</note> that he would blowe vpon his vineyard, that we may bring forth better fruite and preuent the iudgements that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise are like to fall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in that God is so patient
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:176348:93"/> towards vs we are taught to exercise our selues in patience in respect of God when we are afflicted and corrected by him. For when he laies his hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, we may not be angrie, fret, chafe, and rage, but quiet our hearts in his will, though the crosse be grieuous for measure, and long for continuance. This patience to God-ward is tearmed in scripture by an excellent name, <hi>The Silence of the heart,</hi> wherby the heart without repining subiects it selfe to the will of God in all things. Psal. 4.4. <hi>Examine your hearts vpon your bed &amp; be still.</hi> And 37.7. <hi>be silent to Iehoua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, if God be thus patient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men, we againe must be patient one towards another: as Paul saith,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.32. Col. 3.12,</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare one another, and forgiue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as God for Christs sake forgaue you. The faith of the mercifull pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of God cannot but breede and bring foorth in vs patience and long
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:176348:94"/> suffering in regard of anger and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</p>
            <p>Lastly, in that God calls vs to saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with great patience, we must suffer our selues to be called, and runne the race of our saluation with like pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. We must heare the word and <hi>bring forth fruit with patience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 8.</note> We must pray without fainting and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking repulse as the woman of Canaan did:<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> and therefore with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Our hope must be by patience and the cōfort of the scriptures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.3.</note> In a word, we cannot obtaine the <hi>promises with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out patience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.36.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth and last point to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered is, what is meant by the children of Hierusalem. I answere it thus. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in scripture are taken 4. waies. First, some are children by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: of them read Luke the 3. chapter, where a long genealogie is set downe from Adam to Christ. Secondly, some
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:176348:94"/> are called children by adoption with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out generation. Michal,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.13. cum 21.8.</note> that neuer bare child to her death, is <hi>said to beare fiue to Adriel:</hi> because shee did adopt his children, and bring them vp as her owne. Thirdly, some are called chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in regard of <hi>legall succession</hi> in title to this or that thing.<note place="margin">2. King. 24.17. 1. Chro. 3.16.</note> Thus Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias who indeed was vncle to Iehoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim, is said be <hi>the sonne of Iehoakim:</hi> because he did succeed Iehoakim, (as beeing the next of the blood) in the kingdome.<note place="margin">Ier. 23.30. Math. 1.12.</note> Ieconias or Conias <hi>was childlesse:</hi> and yet he is said <hi>to beget Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathiel:</hi> because Salathiel, was to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in the kingdome of Iuda, in that he was the next of Dauids house. Lastly, men, in that they appertaine to any thing or place, as children doe to their parents, are called children there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Thus men are called <hi>children of light, of darkenesse, of sinne, of wrath.</hi> Thus Hierusalem is called the <hi>daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:176348:95"/> of Sion.</hi> And in this text citizens, the inhabitants of Hierusalem, are called the children thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the Rebellion of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem: now followes the punishment in these words: <hi>Behold your habitation shall be left vnto you desolate:</hi> or thus, your house, that is, both cittie and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as it is in the next chapter) shall be left vnto you as a wildernesse.</p>
            <p>Here we must first obserue that the punishmēt of Ierusalēs rebellion is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed desolation both of citie &amp; Tēple. And the right consideration of it is of great vse. For this desolation is as it were a looking glasse to this our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish nation, in which we may see our future condition; except we repent of our vnthankefulnesse to God for his mercies, and shewe better fruits of the gospell, then commonly we doe. The old world little regarded the ministery of Nohe the preacher of righteousnes,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:176348:95"/> and was destroyed by an vniuersall flood. It is a generall decree of God, <hi>The Gentiles and kingdomes that will not serue thee shall perish,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 60.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>and be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly destroyed.</hi> If God spare not the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches, he will much lesse spare vs that are but wild branches, if we neglect &amp; lightly esteeme the gospel of life, as men euery where cōmonly doe.</p>
            <p>Secondly the desolation of Hierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem may be a glasse to euery one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, who in these daies of Gods mercifull visitation, sets the ministerie of the gospell at naught, or lightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects it; for vnlesse such persons amend and that betime, vtter desolation will befall both them and their families. God hath passed his sentence, <hi>they that withdrawe themselues from God shall perish.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 73.27.</note> Nowe they withdrawe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues from God, that cannot abide to haue fellowship with him in his word, and to bring themselues in subiection
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:176348:96"/> thereto. Thirdly, it appeares hence by the contrarie, that the stabilitie of all kingdomes stands in the obedience of the gospell of Christ: for Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is most sure and stable, against which nothing can preuaile. And whē the Gospell is obeyed in any kingdom, it is (as it were) founded in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
            <p>Moreouer this desolation is both perpetuall and terrible: it is perpetuall, that is, to the last iudgement. For Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem must be trode vnder foote, <hi>till the time of the Gentiles be fulfilled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21.24.25.</note> and that is, till there be signes in the sunne and moone, and the powers of heauen be shaken, and that is immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the last iudgement. Hence I gather that there is no cittie of Hierusalem nor Temple now standing. It will be said, that since the destruction thereof they might haue beene reedified. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, by reason of this curse of God, it
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:176348:96"/> cannot so be. Three 100. and 30. yeres after the death of Christ,<note place="margin">Ruffini Iust. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c. 38.</note> the Iewes by the leaue and helpe of Iulian the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, went about to build again their temple and cittie, but their worke was ouerthrowne, and they hindred by thunder &amp; lightening, &amp; earthquakes, and many of them slaine thereby. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine it may be said, that there is a citty now standing that is called Hierusalē. I answer, it is either Hierusalem in his ruines, or the cittie Bethara, fensed and walled by Elius Adrianus. Secondly by this it appeares, that the warres that were made heretofore for the recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Holy land, and of Ierusalem, were in vaine. This enterprize was the pollicie of the Pope that he might the better seate himselfe in Europe. And there was little good to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for in the place that God had accursed with perpetuall desolation. Thirdly by this it appeares, that pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:176348:97"/> made to the Holy land are su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious. And lastly I gather hence, that Antichrist shall not raigne in the Temple at Ierusalem. This is but a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish fiction. For how is it possible for him to sit in a Temple, that is vtterly destroied, in such sort, that stone doth not lie vpon stone. It is obiected, that Antichrist shall destroy the two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God <hi>in the Citie in vvhich Christ was crucified.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 11.8.</note> I answer, Christ is as well crucified in his members as in his own person:<note place="margin">Act. 9.5.</note> &amp; thus he was &amp; is stil crucified in Rome: and in respect of his members more crucified in Rome then in Ierusalem.</p>
            <p>Againe, this desolation was most terrible, and the tribulation thereof so great,<note place="margin">Math. 24.21.</note> that the like was neuer since the beginning of the world. Histories written thereof declare as much. For the citie was at the first besieged by the armie of Titus Vespasianus, called the Abomination of desolation, and it was
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:176348:97"/> withal compassed with a wall that had 13. castles in it to command the whole citie. In the time of the siege, the Iewes were oppressed with a grieuous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: in which their foode was olde shooes, old leather, old hay, &amp; the dung of beasts. There died partly of the sword, &amp; partly of the famine an eleuē hundred thousand of the poorer sort: two thousand in one night were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowelled aliue: sixe thousand were burned in a porch of the Temple: the whole citie was sacked and burnt, and laid leuell to the ground: and nintie sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thousand taken captiues, and to be applied to base and miserable seruice. This horrible desolation, must teach vs to dread and feare God, and to yeeld vnfained subiection to Christ. And as the psalmist saith,<note place="margin">Psal. 2.12.</note>
               <hi>to kisse the sonne least he be angrie,</hi> and we perish in the way, when his wrath shall suddenly burne.</p>
            <p>Touching this desolation there be
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:176348:98"/> three things done by Christ. First he determines it, saying, <hi>Your house shal be left vnto you desolate.</hi> Hence I gather that there is a prouidence of God, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching things that come to passe. That is one point. The second is, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposition of kingdomes for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, continuance, and ende, is of God. <hi>The God of heauen</hi> (saith Cyrus) <hi>hath giuen me all the kingdoms of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 1.2.</note> And Daniel to Nabuchadnezzar,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.37.</note>
               <hi>The God of heauen hath giuen thee king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, power, and glorie.</hi> And the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing vpon the wall in the sight of Baltasher was to this effect,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.26.</note>
               <hi>Thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is numbered,</hi> for continuance of yeares: <hi>it is waighed</hi> and found light in respect of the sinnes of the people: and <hi>it is deuided</hi> to the Medes &amp; Persians. This must teach all good subiects in England, to lift vp their hearts to God, for the continuance of peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to this Church and land.</p>
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:176348:98"/>
            <p>Secondly, Christ reueales the desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hierusalem and that certainely: yea, he determines the very particular time.<note place="margin">Math. 24.34.</note>
               <hi>This generation</hi> (saith he) <hi>shall not passe till all these things be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:</hi> And according to this reuelation &amp; prediction of Christ, al things came to passe. For within the compasse of 40. yeares after it was destroied. Hence I gather that this gospell of Matthew and the rest are the very word of God, on this manner. That which foretells particular things to come certainely &amp; truely, is of God: but the gospels fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell particular things to come certainly and truely, as in this place we see: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and lastly, Christ labours to bring the Iewes to a serious considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their punishment, whē he saith, <hi>Behold.</hi> For he doth as it were take thē by the hand, and bring them to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent view of their miserie. And thus he
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:176348:99"/> hath alwaies dealt with his people frō the beginning. Yea thus he dealt with Adam before his fall, when he saide, <hi>If thou eate the forbidden fruit in dying thou shalt die.</hi> This serious considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deserued punishments, is of great vse.<note place="margin">Amos 4.12.</note> It is an occasion of repentance to many. It is a meanes, if not of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet of restraint of open vices. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the consideration of euerlasting punishments, is a meanes to make vs patiently beare lesser crosses that befall vs in this life. And therefore it were to be wished, that mē now a daies would seriously thinke and speake of hell, and of the paines thereof. For then there would be more amendmēt then there is. But this good is hindered partly by blindnes of minde, and partly by false imaginations,<note place="margin">Isa. 28.18.</note> that the iudgements and punishments of God may easily be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scaped.</p>
            <trailer>DEO GLORIA.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176348:99"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>